<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Elymas the sorcerer, or, A memorial towards the discovery of the bottom of this Popish-Plot and how far his R. Highness's directors have been faithful to his honour and interest, or the peace of the nation : publish'd upon occasion of a passage in the late Dutchess of York's declaration for changing her religion / by Tho. Jones ...</title>
            <author>Jones, Thomas, 1622?-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47078</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1915</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12576542</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12576542</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63595</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47078)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 962:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Elymas the sorcerer, or, A memorial towards the discovery of the bottom of this Popish-Plot and how far his R. Highness's directors have been faithful to his honour and interest, or the peace of the nation : publish'd upon occasion of a passage in the late Dutchess of York's declaration for changing her religion / by Tho. Jones ...</title>
                  <author>Jones, Thomas, 1622?-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Jones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [1]</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1]</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63595:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63595:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Elymas the Sorcerer:</hi> OR, A MEMORIAL Towards the DISCOVERY Of the <hi>Bottom</hi> of this Popiſh-PLOT, And how far his R. HIGHNESS's Directors have been Faithful to his Honour and Intereſt, or the Peace of the NATION. Publiſh'd upon occaſion of a Paſſage in the Late Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs of <hi>YORK's</hi> Declaration for changing her RELIGION.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>THO: JONES</hi> ſometime Domeſtick and Naval Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to his R. Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Cur aliquid vidi? Cur noxia Lumina feci?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>12, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>My Strength is made perfect weakneſs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Jones,</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63595:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63595:2"/>
            <head>A Memorial towards the Diſcovery of the Original of this Popiſh-Plot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>MOnſieur Maimbourg,</hi> in his Hiſtory of <hi>Calviniſme,</hi> very lately put out, this preſent year 1682, in ſeveral Editions, recites therein with great Catholick boaſt and hopes, A Declaration of her late Highneſs the Dutcheſs of <hi>York,</hi> of the Reaſons and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives ſhe had to change her Religion.</p>
            <p>I regarded one paſſage therein, more upon my own experience, than the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of a Stranger, which juſtified a ſuſpition, I endur'd long trouble for many years, to adhere to, out of fidelity to my Church and Country, though ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laſh'd with the Imputations of Pride and diſobedience for it, for which I am to bleſs. The paſſage is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J'ay eſte particulierement &amp; fortement convaincue de la preſence reele de Jeſus-Chriſt au Saint Sacrement de l' Autel, de l'infaillibilite de l' Egliſe, de la Confeſſion &amp; de la priere pour les morts. J'ay voulu conferer de ces marieres par maniere, dentretien avec les deux plus habiles Eveſques que nous ayons en Angleterre: &amp; tous deux m'ont avoue ingenument qu'ily a bien des choſes dans l'Egliſe Romaine qu'il ſeroit a deſirer que l' Egliſe Anglicane euſt toujours obſervees, comme la Confeſſion qu'on ne ſcau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roit deſavouer que <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieu meſme n'ait commandee, &amp; la priere pour les morts, qui eſt une des plus authentiques &amp; les plus anciennes pratiques de la Religion Chreſtienne; que pour eux ils s'en ſervoient en particulier ſans en faire une profeſſion publique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Comme je preſſois un de ces Eveſques ſur les autres points de concroverſe, &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalement ſur la preſence reele de Jeſus Chriſt au Saint Sacrament de l' Autel: il me repondit librement, que s'il eſtoit Catholique, il ne voudroit pas changer de Religion mais qu'ayant eſte eleve dans une Egliſe dans laquelle il croyoit avoir tout ce qui eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſaire au ſalus, &amp; y ayant receu ſon Bapteſme, il ne croyoit pas la pouvoir quitter ſans un grand ſcandale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tout ce diſcours neſervit qu'a augmenter le deſir ardent que j'avois de me rendre Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, &amp; je ſentis des peines interieures &amp; d'horribles inquietudes enſuite de la con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation que j'eus avec ces deux Eveſques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I was particularly and ſtrongly convinced of the real preſence of Jeſus Chriſt in the Holy Sacrament of the Altar, of the Infallibility of the Church, Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Prayer for the Dead, I was willing to conferr of theſe matters by way of Diſcourſe, with the Two moſt able Biſhops that we have in <hi>England,</hi> and both confeſt to me ingeniouſly, That <hi>there are many things in the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>which it was to be wiſhed that the Church of</hi> England <hi>had ſtill obſerved, as Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which it could not be denied but that God had commanded it, and Prayer for the Dead which is one of the moſt authentick and Antient Practices of the Chriſtian Religion; but as to themſelves they made uſe thereof in private without making pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick profeſſion thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As I preſſed one of theſe Biſhops upon the other points of Controverſy, and principally on the Real Preſence of Jeſus Chriſt in the Holy Sacrament of the Altar, he anſwered me freely, that <hi>were he a Catholick, he would not change Religion; but that having been educated in a Church in which he believed there was all that was neceſſary to Salvation, and there having received his Baptiſme, he thought he could not quit it without great Scandal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this diſcourſe ſerved but to increaſe the Ardent deſire which I had to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Catholick; and I felt inward Pains and horrible diſquiets after the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation I had with theſe Two Biſhops.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Author of the Apology in behalf of the Papiſts, Printed in</hi> 1666, <hi>(who well knew me and the cauſe of my ſufferings) dropt an Early Intimation of the like Import:</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:63595:3"/>
            <q>We dare with ſubmiſſion ſay, Let a Publick Invitation be put up againſt any Party whatſoever; Nay, againſt the Reverend Biſhops themſelves, and ſome malicious (in his Lordſhips ſenſe) Informer, or other, will alledge that, which may be far better to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal.</q>
            <p>There are but few to be found, ſo forſaken of God and their own Reaſons, as are not able to diſcern and allow, that Secret Enemies are far more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to all Men and Communities, than open and profeſl'd: and that Men hate to be betrayed worſe, than to be Deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>They therefore that countenance or cover the Maſquerade Enemies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> prove themſelves to be of the ſame pernicious conſpiracy; the greater they are in Place and Power, the greater is the danger to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick from them, and their detection therefore the greater ſervice and Glory.</p>
            <p>Her late Highneſs expreſſes not what Biſhops thoſe Two were in Particular, whom all ſober Proteſtants muſt look on, as the betrayers of her Soul, and this Church. It ſeems duty and fidelity to our Church and Nation, to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute Intelligence and Obſervations to detect them farther. They are not in <hi>Reaſon</hi> Fathers, who are condemned Perſons in <hi>Law.</hi> And the danger and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of their ill example is the leſs, becauſe they never ſhewed ſo much Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Integrity, as to juſtifie before the world their new Perſwaſions by Pen, or open Practice, or Reſignation. A <hi>Papiſt</hi> or a <hi>Mahometan</hi> that is ſincere and Reſolute in the profeſſion of his errour, ſhews more Religon, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, than the moſt Reverend two fac'd Renegado, that's falſe to his Faith, and truſt, and Countrey, for wordly Intereſt. And Indeed, he that is ſo falſe to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, will hardly be true to any other; Therefore <hi>Campanella</hi> adviſes to chuſe for confeſſor <hi>non qui te diligit, ſed qui diligit animam Suam,</hi> ſuch who loves his own Soul, not thee.</p>
            <p>To theſe <hi>Judas</hi>'s amongſt our Apoſtles is cheiflly owing the preſent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and Rediviſion of theſe flouriſhing Kingdoms by new Fears, and fewds: and not a little perhaps to the Eternal Frailties of great ones, that had rather be <hi>Pleaſ'd</hi> than <hi>Lovd.</hi> How happy were it for the Nation, if ſuch carnal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliers for the ſake of Grandeur, were as hateful to our Princes, as they are to God and the reſt of Mankinde, I have no better account to give to God and the World, of the latter part of my life, than ſome zeal and Adventures againſt ſuch Betrayers, which I have preferred before all worldly offers and Peace. I ſhould therefore hide my Candle under a Buſhel, If I did not give ſome acount, and communicate to the world, theſe enſuing Paſſages at eaſt, which have paſſed from me, to his <hi>R. H.</hi> Chaplains, and Officers, and ſeveral Reverend Biſhops, before, and long before, <hi>Maimbourg</hi>'s Book came out, which I humbly recommend to all true hearted, and Generous Sons and Fathers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to peruſe, and freely to judge of their own, and countries concerns, and my weak, but ſincere Endeavours, as their Conſciences ſhall direct: being ever firm to their Loyal Communion, and reſolv'd through Gods Grace to perſevere; though with ſome difference from other pretenders, or this Invincible infirmity, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to believe, (though never much for Perſecution) any R. Biſhop, who were falſe to his Church, where he enjoys ſuch maintenance, and honour, to deſerve Hanging infinitely better, than any lawleſs trayterous <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> who would avowedly deſtroy it, out of Blind Zeal and ſidelity to his own.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>A Letter to Doctor <hi>W.</hi> Chaplain to his <hi>R. H.</hi> Dated April the 5th <hi>1682.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOu have had now time enough from <hi>February</hi> 23 and ſome of your Brethren in the ſame myſtery, moniſh'd alike, much longer ſpace, to conſult your Duty and ſafety.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not, and I think, ought not to publiſh any of your Letters that you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63595:3"/>have, or may ſend in anſwer, without your leave and deſire; nor my ſecond part as yet conſiſting of more particulars from firſt to laſt, as long as I find ſo little exception againſt the firſt, or indeed none at all, that either is or can be with any Truth. Which I ſee no reaſon therefore why I may not Print, as well for publick Information and Benefit, (with ſubmiſſion) to be tendered above all ſmaller reſpects, as for neceſſary Private vindication of my good name, before I dye; which next to good Conſcience, hath an Immortal, Spiritual exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to be fairly preſerved in minds, againſt all Temporal hindrance; as alſo for a Lawful and laudable Intereſt and fellow-feeling from Innumerable True Proteſtants throughout the Nation, upon knowledge of my Caſe, which by two much Patience and tenderneſs toward unnatural and diſguis'd Beings, I have ſo long diſregarded and wav'd.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe you may apprehend me as an Enemy for minding and ſetting you upon ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Truth, I ſhall therefore forbear to adviſe you: But the Apoſtle directs us to ſuffer, if Gods will be ſo, in a good work, rather than in an Evil: And I take it to be a better work, to contribute to ſave Church and Countrey, though with Trouble and Danger, than to be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to either, with Peace and Plenty. Which choice hath been my ſupport and ſolace for many years, againſt the ſubtel and Mercileſs aſſaults and preſſures of Catholick Zeal, tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling Antichriſtianly, as uſual, upon the Laws of God and Man, on Faith and Truth, and Conſcience, and Honour, and Civility, and Humanity, and fair and Generous Hoſtility. For what greater ſatisfaction to a Subject, or Glory to a Prince, (let <hi>France</hi> now be judge) than to be Gods Inſtruments to deliver our Church and Country from Spiritual Captivity? or what greater blot or Curſe, than to be Slaves to Knaves to betray a delivered Nation anew into it?</p>
                  <p>If I therefore reccomend to you the ſame hazards and comforts I my ſelf have choſen, and preferred before all offers, and Sums, and greater Princely favour and Intereſt, than all can well pretend to, wherein can you complain of any unworthineſs in me, but that I have diſcharged the part of an honeſt and a Loyal Subject, and becauſe Proteſtant is not ſo pleaſing to you, of your</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Dated</hi> 
                        <date>April 5. 82.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>For the Reverend Dr. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to his R. H. Rector of near <hi>Malborough.</hi>
                  </trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Chriſtian Friend <hi>THO. JONES.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Another to the ſame Perſon, Dated <hi>February, 1681.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Suppoſe I have given ſufficient proof to you, and the world, of patience and quietneſs, under long hard uſage, from 1664 to this preſent, without the paſſion of a Troden Worm. Not for want of life, or ſence, but out of regard and tenderneſs to Adverſaries and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertors, and a dumb grief and aſtoniſhment at the ſad condition of this Chuch upon its reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, to have, as I much ſuſpected, diſguiſed Wolves amongſt its chief Paſtors and Watchmen, not to be concealed without great danger, nor diſcovered without greater ſcandal and confuſion.</p>
                  <p>The oppreſſion it ſelf, though reaching (not directly to blood, but) to ſeveral more precious Lives, was not ſo fore and inſupportable, as the unkindneſs and treachery, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting wrath and reprobation, that attended it, without bounds, or Sun-ſets, or any vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible cauſe or Provocation, the Spirit and cloathing of <hi>Calvin,</hi> dexterouſly concealing from me, and others, the killing Red Letter within.</p>
                  <p>Neither was it a pleaſant Riddle, to find the Fathers of my own Church to Execute Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh threats and predictions againſt me, and that in a myſterious prevalent oppoſition to his R. Highneſs, who overruled ſeveral times for me, againſt them, and his late Ducheſs, and Commanded me to depend upon his favour and protection to the end; in ſo much, that my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> ſent for me on purpoſe, to declare that the Dutcheſs deſired him to trouble me no more, becauſe the Duke was ſo firm unto me; and deſired me to acquieſce and he would acquieſce, and being taken off my watch and guard, I was immediately deſtroyed for my Faith.</p>
                  <p>Neither was it eaſie then with me to believe, what principles might neceſſitate, or legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate ſuch methods, till ſubſequent revolts gave ſome light, firſt of her late Highneſs, (won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at in 1670.) by her Father in his Letters, and foretold by me to ſeveral Private Friends, in 1666. from ſome paſſages in concurrence with him and my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> to ſuppreſs and diſcourage, and at laſt to Sacrifice me to ſome of the other Chappel at St.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63595:4"/>
                     <hi>James</hi>'s, for no other cauſe, but my executing her Orders againſt Popery in her Family; whereby I conjectured and inferred, her own Religion would be her next oblation. But that of his Highneſs when rumoured ſhortly after, I could not ſo eaſily believe, becauſe he was, or ſeemed ignorant of their deſigns, and defended me againſt their aſſaults, though his Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Directors; unleſs it may be thought, that they who were able to make him quit his Promiſes, might alſo be able to make him quit his Faith, taking an old Proverb to their aſſiſtance, <hi>My Mother loves to be killed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The pain and ſmart of ſuffering being well over, and worn out by long uſe and familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the unfading comforts of Integrity remain. And I bleſs God that he hath given me Grace to chuſe Affliction rather than Sin; and to ſuffer in Innocence, and for no other cauſe, but my fidelity to this Apoſtolical Proteſtant Church providentially Reſtored and Re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, by our Renowned Princes of Brittiſh Line; (which God may order for its ſtrength in his time) and that I was no Scandal or Stumbling-block to my Prince by carnal comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with his frailties for advantage, but adhear'd to my duty and truth againſt all Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations of worldly intereſt and Dignity on the one hand, and extreameſt hardſhips on the other; that the adverſe diſſenting party cannot boaſt that none of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are ſo firm againſt Popery as themſelves: Though I doubt not there are many thouſand right Sons of this Church in obſcurity, and many in dignity, that have the ſame Integrity, though not the ſame circumſtances and tryal, believing the Truth by private Chriſtians, may be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter defended by patience and truſt in God, than by diſcontents and its effects; though all muſt confeſs, that Perſons in publick Truſt, may, and ought to proceed by other meaſures, for the juſt defence of themſelves and their Dependants, as the fear and courage of all Creatures is not the ſame, when they have, or have not, young ones to defend.</p>
                  <p>And I found much Art and Endeavours uſed to deprive me of the honour of my Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and the credit of my Teſtimony, by miſrepreſenting me to my Prince and Maſter, and to the World, in characters not what themſelves believed, but what he or they might hate or deſpiſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That I was a <hi>Preſbyterian,</hi> and an Enemy to the Governours and Government of this Church; upon which iſſue I deſired a Tryal, but this they ſoon waved; it being known unto them by Teſtimonials, upon my admiſſion to his R. H. Service, and otherways, how I act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſuffered upon the contrary principle (being Epiſcopally Ordained in 1654. and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing others of Parts and Fortunes to be then ſo Ordained) with conſiderable Service to this Church, and check to its Adverſaries and greateſt Regicides, in the times of Uſurpation, though not ſo violent, as the mode is, after they were down.</p>
                  <p>And though I had the honour (to uſe a Phraſe) and perhaps the ſole honour and danger of expreſſing at Aſſizes in the way of my Calling, my deteſtation of the Murder of the King, and the oppreſſion of his Party, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And owned my Principles before the Bloody Judge concerned, when I was then call'd before him, yet I found more clearneſs and huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity from him, than from your Enigmatical Party; for he offered me protection in my Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Principles, on condition I medled not with State-matters, as he ſtiled thoſe publick Sins. Neither was it unknown to them, that his Highneſs writ in my behalf for the Deanry of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> upon ſuch merits, atteſted by the Biſhop himſelf, and the chiefeſt of thoſe parts, where the paſſages are yet well known and remembred: while ſome of you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in your more ſafe receſs abroad, through diſtruſt in God, or diſcontent, Bartered ſome of the Articles of your Faith for your worldly convenience, or Revenge; and I Expected not, to be accounted a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> for adhearing faithfully to the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt Popery by any true Proteſtancy; yet always believed Proteſtants of your Stamp, with our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reclaimable Diſſenters, did Equally promote the Deſigns of <hi>Rome,</hi> with, or againſt their Wills, as outwitted or trappaned by their contrary Paſſions.</p>
                  <p>And perhaps ſome of your chiefs have Artificially promoted and indulged, this their diſſent and ſeparation, ſo uſeful to <hi>Papiſts</hi> in dividing Proteſtancy, and ſo befriending <hi>Athieſts</hi> in ſlighting our Liturgy and publick worſhip and Miniſtry, when at the ſame time they might be thought to wiſh them but one neck, from their good will; And I was denied the ſame time the benefit of the falſe accuſations that cloathed me in their Skin.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63595:4"/>
                  <p>The next Objection that I heard, did Alienate both their Highneſies from me, was my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the Sacrament to the Family on Aſſention day, 1666, becauſe the Dutcheſs was not there to receive, and that therefore I ſcorned to give it to the Reſt. And the Teſtimony of Several Perſons of quality and vertue, who then and there at the time in queſtion, Actually Received the Sacrament at my hands, and are ſtill Living and remembring, would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffice; for your Party, my Accuſers knew the truth as well as any of them, and that they had excluded me from all manner of Officiating before the Dutcheſs long before; and the ſmall interuption that was, about half a minute, between the firſt and ſecond Service, was from the contrivance, I obſerved, of many of you together making uſe of the Sacrament, when you wanted other means to deſtroy your Brother. This alſo was waved; however now and then inſiſted on, and alledg'd in private behind my Back, by your Party, againſt their Conſciences, when they had no other anſwer to make to a Queſtion asked them, <hi>Why did the Duke caſt off ſuch a Servant?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Third exception they had a mind to inſiſt on, but that it could not brook Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was, for ſpeaking Irreverently of the Biſhop of <hi>Winton</hi>'s prohibiting my Preaching at Sea: but this alſo was ſolemnly waved by him, before the late Arch-Biſhop, at the Dean of the Chappels Lodgings at <hi>White-Hall.</hi> There being a manifeſt Treachery, in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, who perverted my words and deſign; and a great irregularity in that action of my Lord of <hi>Wintons</hi> againſt the Fleet-Statute, which required Preaching, and the Seamen's needs, and good Example in the Fleet, and againſt particular Orders to the contrary from his Highneſs, through his Almoner to me, and being in no truſt or ſuperiority over me, in Relation to the Sea, only out of a particular pique againſt me, for no Cauſe but what you know, and I ſuſpect: yet the only pretence for my ruine at firſt, was, my want of ſubmiſſion to this charge, which himſelf had wav'd; neither was I wanting to ask his pardon for any occaſion of diſpleaſure given him howſoever, being deſired and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thereto by the D. my Dioceſan, and a great Friend.</p>
                  <p>I heard of ſome other general Exceptions againſt me, that I was Proud, and Turbulent, but for no particular Reaſon as I could ever learn, but that I was not ſo humble, and Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as to connive, and conſent to ſuffer this Church to be wrong'd, and undermin'd, but was ſteddy and Faithful, in my Poſt, and Truſt; which was the Reaſon perhaps, that on falſlly ſwore for your Party, that I delighted to contend with great Biſhops, who yet lived not long after it, to enjoy the Intereſt, and benefit of his Swearing; For I had decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the contrary, that I delighted not to contend with great or ſmall, or equal, with my Reaſons for each.</p>
                  <p>Another, and not the leaſt, was, that I ſhould call <hi>Mr.</hi> M. a <hi>Court Jack-pudding;</hi> and I confeſs I told him, that drollery was not wit, but a <hi>Jack-Pudding</hi> dialect, when I obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him countenanc'd to Buffoon, and abuſe me (and alſo my Man) daily and publickly, when I was at the ſame time as frequently extold by the Duke and Dutcheſs: but the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman ſince asked me forgiveneſs, ond confeſſed his wrong, and who had ſet him on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhewing more ſigns of true Chriſtianity, and a ſenſe of Conſcience, then I obſerved in the Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of your Party, who wanted the Manners and Loyalty, that is obſerved in <hi>Noah,</hi> who curſt not <hi>Cbam</hi> (though in fault) becauſe Bleſſed by God juſt before, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.15. with 1.</p>
                  <p>And to reckon all as I have heard, or can Remember, (my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> Threatning that he would ſearch me to my Cradle) one of his Lordſhips Exceptions againſt me, out of his Simplicity and Ingratitude, was my Extraction out of <hi>Wales,</hi> which I was not aſhamed to own, (though born and bred in <hi>England,</hi> for reaſons <hi>then</hi> given his Lordſhip: From the Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Loyalty of the People, among whom he had his firſt preferment; and <hi>ſince</hi> to the World, in my ſmall Book againſt a Poſition, publickly aſſerted by his Lordſhip (as I was credibly informed) that <hi>Rome</hi> was Mother Church to <hi>England,</hi> the admitting where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I fear'd, from my obſervations, might operate upon his Highneſs Inſtability.</p>
                  <p>And ſince I hear of another of his Lordſhips exceptions about my being no Schollar, which I know not well how to anſwer, nor whether it be worth; though upon no other ſcore, but the contrary character, and that not ordinary; Was I recommended for his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Service, by ſome of the moſt Learned in our Nation; and had been Chaplain before
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63595:5"/>to the Kings Preſident and Council, in the parts I liv'd in, upon the Recommendation of ſome Reverend Biſhops, who knew me better? And his Lordſhips Objection was anſwered by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of quality and Learning to whom it was made, and who was heretofore of the ſame College with me, <hi>That my Neighbours eſteemed otherwiſe of me in the Univerſity;</hi> and I have reaſons to think that his Lordſhip. ſpoke againſt his own belief and good information to the contrary. I have taken great and conſtant pains, for many years together, to the empair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Sight, not to be culpably Ignorant in any part of Learning belonging to my profeſſion, and I found by the Reſentment of Auditors and Judges, in all publick places of Court or City, or Countrey, wherever I Preached, that my Labour was not miſſpent; and I obſerved a great induſtry in your Party to promote Early, and all along, this Smother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Objection, and to overlay me when I was grown too big. Lord Ch. H. in 1666. about the time of <hi>De Macedo</hi>'s eſcape, and return, ſtop't me from proceeding D. D. without any cauſe, againſt common right, and reſpect to the Duke, and large voluntary promiſes of all Favour made to me a little before, I having more then time, and willing to do all my Exerciſes. Wherein your Party had a Fairer oppertunity to convince me of my Ignorance, if they had truſted to their objection: and was about the ſame time Excluded from Preaching my Dioceſans conſecration Sermon at <hi>Lambeth</hi> (which he requeſted) Two very ominous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications of the Impending Storm (which immediately followed) before half of your Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles againſt me were invented. But afterwards I found Friends alſo diſcouraged from ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of my aſſiſtance in their Pulpits upon occaſions, as wont, and a ſilence deſigned at laſt upon me, and Effected for many years in the Country, as well as at Court, and City, and Sea; and all for no reaſon, as I thought at firſt, but for being obſerved to outpitch your Party in Preaching; Aut it was afterwards made manifeſt, it was not want of Learning, but want of compliance with dark deſigns, (Stiled diſobedence to Superiors) that kept me from Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Dignity; for I would not enſlave and debauch my Conſcience knowingly in the leaſt Sin, for the greateſt advantage in this world; leaſt in time, as I obſerved ſome Inſtances, I ſhould not have the leaſt grain of Conſcience, or Religion, or Honeſty, or Modeſty, or any Truth, or Grace left, which Vertues I prefer'd before all Learning whatſoever, as ends ought to be before means: Which I believed the more to be the true cauſe, and not the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe I obſerved ſome of the greateſt then, and moſt Reverend of your Party, not to Read or Pronounce according to true Grammar and conjugation, their Common Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion over my Head. But if this would put a Period to my trouble, and Diſgrace, from your Party, I would be willing to undergo a ſtrict Examination yet, of my Studies, provided it be in publick, and before others. For I obſerved, when my ſmall Treatiſe came firſt out, (which cured me of this, and the following Imputation, as eaſie as the Philoſopher proved Motion, by walking) what pittiful ſhifts your Party were reduced to uſe, to ſupport their tottering Objection, <hi>He did not write the Book; another writ it for him, at leaſt he writ not the Epiſtle Dedicatory.</hi> &amp;c. And when that would not do, other Arts muſt be uſed to ſuppreſs the Sale, and decry and ſlight the Book, though I received good thanks and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects for the Argument, Levelled to the Capacities I deſign'd it for, from many unconcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and unpenſioned in your Parties deſign againſt me, and thoſe of the moſt Learned of our Engliſh Nation; and of all Degrees, and Dignities, and Qualities, and Profeſſions, and Perſwaſions.</p>
                  <p>I had almoſt forgot the other notable Charge, and Engine, of conſiderable uſe to ſecure your Party, and ſtifle my repute and teſtimony, that was (when all exceptions failed) that I was Mad and Diſtracted, which by their venerable Authority (ſuch was their Power, and Guidance over his Highneſs) they made the Duke believe to be true (in contradiction to his freſh commendations) and many other conſiderable perſons beſides, to my very Great detriment in the world; It being eaſier with well meaning People, to believe me to be Mad, then ſuch perſons to be Lyars; But I could not hear of any Inſtances and Signs of this Diſtemper in me, ſaving Two: The firſt was, the neglecting ſo fair an Intereſt, as I had in the Duke, to adhere to an Opinion; wherein I hope the Duke will, or ought, before any, to forgive and heal me, who venters Infinitely higher upon the like principle; and I did it not without Study, and Oaths, and the Laws, and Councels, and Intereſt of the Nation on my Side. The Second (as nothing can be hid which will not be made known) was, becauſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63595:5"/>they found by my Servant, that I had not been in bed, but in my Cloſet the whole night, before I ſet out for Sea; And he was ſolicited by your party with great offers and promiſes, to ſwear ſomething of that, or any other nature againſt me, for that I was a falling perſon, and not like to help him; and I heard others were encouraged by the other Chappel to ſecond your party in promoting this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, which none of your ſelves did at all believe, though you abus'd the credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and weakneſs of others, to give it countenance, againſt your conſciences.</p>
                  <p>For this charge (as any wiſe and good man may eaſily diſcern) is contradictory and inconſiſtent with their former Articles and Subſequent Actions at Law againſt me, for who ever heard of a <hi>non compos mentis</hi> Accus'd to Princes, or Sued at Law for expreſſions? Therefore my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> ought in Reaſon and Logick to reſtore me either to my ſences, or my money: In all conſcience to both; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be Innocent or Guilty; for wherefore ſhould he have pleaded his privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (and that againſt his promiſe to the contrary in writing) to withhold 300 l. or (600. l. as was proved at Kings Bench,) recovered againſt a diſtracted man, for certain words miſconſtrued and perverted? and which he knows are ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered at Law in part againſt his Farmers, (who flye the Country) upon his il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal proceedings, himſelf hardly eſcapeing being fined by the Court.</p>
                  <p>When all accuſations failed, my Ruine was contrived by way of preferment, not to <hi>Bedlam,</hi> in purſuance of the former calumny, but in confutation of it, into a conſiderable living in order to a Biſhoprick, <hi>viz. Llandyrnog</hi> in <hi>dyffrin-cluid</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> which the Biſhops of <hi>Bangor</hi> uſually held in <hi>commendam,</hi> for their conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Reſidence and the <hi>Sine-Cures</hi> which were held in <hi>commendam</hi> by Biſhop <hi>Roberts</hi> deceaſed, and were more conſiſtent with my Reſidence in the Dukes ſervice, were diſpoſed to others to make room for an Objection of Inconfiſtency) and I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to repair from Sea to <hi>Oxford</hi> to accept of the ſaid living, when the Roads were all Infected, and 9000. <hi>per</hi> week dyed at <hi>London,</hi> by which I was to paſs; upon my arrival firſt to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and next to my living, I diſcerned a double ſnare therein, one to ſupplant me out of the Dukes ſervice, (as I was kindly inform'd by one of your party;) which the Duke upon my application, aſſured ſhould never be, and ordered me to take out the Seales. Another, no likelyhood of enjoying it quietly, by Incommoding my <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> whereupon I petitioned to relinquiſh it, but was over ruled and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed unto it, as a Princely proviſion: Whereupon my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> inſtigated my <hi>Dioceſan</hi> againſt me at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> that I, or his Lordſhip was the greateſt Rogue in <hi>England,</hi> and threatned me by another, that he would make the three Kingdoms too hot to hold me, by a third Reverend perſon, that he would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute me whitherſoever I went to the utmoſt of his power: And I anſwered, that then I muſt put on a patience as large as his power; now there was no ſore touched as yet, adequate to this winching.</p>
                  <p>Whereupon my <hi>Dioceſan</hi> having a declar'd liking to my living, (and I denying now to exchange, or quit it, as dear bought,) and finding I had great Enemies, and no protection, joyn'd with your party, by new contrivances,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of a frivolous controverſy about a reading ſeat, (not to be paraleld in this Age or Nation,)</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of an Action of <hi>Scandalum Magnatum</hi> to ſecond it, to wreſt both my living and calling from me, which he wanted not power to effect, by the Oaths of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, (which I knew to be as falſe, as the accuſations of their Principals to heave me out of Court) and therefore could not, and would not accept of their 300. l.Verdict to be remitted, nor of greater offers, to ſubmit, and allow them to be true: yea I heard their encouraged Agents offered them oaths that would take away my life, which they have not produced before Authority from that time to this. So that no Innocence, or Vigilance, could ſecure me from their power, in that Place and Station, where I was wholy a ſtranger; and thus for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, and thoſe my beſt, I have been expoſed to live without imployment or maintenance, or credit, or peace, upon the relief of my next Relations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this preferment, with the long trouble and charge attending it (which ended at laſt through the help of Providence in their ſhame and diſappointment) was rendred inſignificant, and worſe than none at all, againſt the declared Intentions of his Highneſs to the contrary, if not againſt his Princely Honour and Juſtice,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63595:6"/>who counts it part of Glory, you know, to be a good Maſter and a Man of his word.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding it was known to your party, that I had waved a good offer to adhere to the Dukes ſervice (counting it improper to deſert a Prince on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for advantage) which to another proved a Dignity of about a <hi>Thouſand pounds per annum,</hi> and might have proved ſo to me in all probability, neither did I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume at firſt to ſeek His Highneſs ſervice, but was ſought for, being a Stranger to all in his Family, as likewiſe to thoſe Learned Prebends of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> upon whoſe reports of ſome Sermons Preached at <hi>Weſtminiſter</hi>-Abby, I was enquired for by the Dukes <hi>Almoner</hi> who had order from Her late Highneſs to enquire out a fit Perſon to take the conſtant charge of her Family, while the other four Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains were to wait quarterly in her Cloſet, and to Preach by turns with me in the Chappel throughout the year, all our Salaries being <hi>Fifty pound per annum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as I came in by Providence, and without the precarious help of intereſt, ſo I continued in the Family with good love and reſpect, and (ſeeing you force me) with far more then you, or thoſe of your party, my equals, had, as may, if need appear by ſeveral inſtances, till that in 1664. the Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> began to frown upon me, upon my relieving De. <hi>Macedo &amp;c.</hi> and to ſet you, and others to decry me, and to make a new diſtinction, and difference between the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines (which ſince my letter in <hi>June</hi> laſt to Dr. <hi>T.</hi> is endeavoured to be revived, and ſupported, as I hear, but with poor and lame ſucceſs, and after the Blot was hit) and to report me to be no chaplain to the Duke (to pleaſe your envy and his own deſign) but as it were an Impoſtor for aſſumeing it, (which I remember did not a litle greive me) and that becauſe, as was objected, I came not in through my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> of whoſe right to Introduce Chaplains ſolely, I was then, and am to this day Ignorant, but ſince gueſs'd at the deſign; who therefore cauſed my Salary to be reduced from <hi>Fifty pound</hi> to <hi>Forty,</hi> becauſe he was not conſenting to my admiſſion; Though Dr. <hi>Killigrew,</hi> His Highneſs <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Triplet,</hi> both his Lotdſhips good Friends, gave it under their hands, which I delivered his Lordſhip, that his Lordſhip was privy and conſenting to my ſetlement and ſalary according to <hi>Fifty pound,</hi> but his Lordſhip anſwered, he was not bound to follow their teſtimony againſt his own conſcience, yet the Duke over ruled in this matter by his order for me; and indeed my place, for Intereſt and Profit, was the more eligible, as I told his Lordſhip. His Highneſs likewiſe ſent me to the late Arch-Biſhop, to ſee me fully ſetled by Law, both in his Service and my Living (for the inconſiſtency thereof was another exception to remove me from him, which themſelves had contrived) who returned his anſwer by me, that he could not underſtand, how one body could be in two places, which His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs over ruled: but how can you expect to thrive, ſaid Sir <hi>A. A.</hi> to me, who have the Arch-Biſhop and Biſhop of <hi>Winton</hi> againſt you?</p>
                  <p>Accordingly ſome other ſecret matter was whiſpred againſt me to his Highneſs by them, which took of his Favour irrecoverably from me, from that time to this.</p>
                  <p>Some years after, when I petitioned His Highneſs for Reſtoration, upon the ſcore of Innocence, or elſe, for common ordinary Juſtice, and equity, between any Maſter and Servant in three particulars,
<list>
                        <item>1. Arrears of Salarie.</item>
                        <item>2. A <hi>Bene diſceſſit</hi> and leave to take another Patron.</item>
                        <item>3. Some reparation of detriment by occaſion of his Service,</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>His Highneſs was graciouſly pleaſed with kind circumſtances, to give me his anſwer by my Lord <hi>Craven,</hi> to this effect, that his Lordſhip doubted not to ſee me ſuddainly made a Biſhop, if I ſubmitted to the Biſhops. And I anſwered I had given His Highneſs Reaſons in Paper, why I could not (becauſe their Terms were indiſpenſably, to renounce my Innocence and Truth, to ſecure and juſtify them) if then ſaid his Lordſhip, you cannot, and will not ſubmit to the Biſhops, His Highneſs's laſt anſwer is, that he can do nothing for you, but as he is directed by the Biſhops, which was agreable to former anſwers of His Highneſs to me, that he referd them matters to the Biſhops, and I heard it from others, of different intereſts, who well knew His Highneſs's mind in this matter: That he would do nothing for me againſt the mind of the Biſhops, but if I could get the Biſhops of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63595:6"/>my ſide, he would be as kind as ever Sr. <hi>W. C. C. W. L. C. M.</hi> Neither would the Biſhops give His Highneſs way to ſhew me Favour, or do me Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, as above, without ſuch ſubmiſſion, which they had not power enough to bring me to, (as I told them, when I was loweſt) and ſo it continues ſtill with me, though the one be in His Grave, the other gone off the Stage, and Biſhop <hi>Blanford</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> (deſired by the Duke to ſearch my cauſe) reported on my behalf in the matter of the reading Pew, againſt my <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> but as to the concern of the greater Biſhops, he thought fit, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>So that I could not well and fully make uſe of a great Patronage within reach, moſt neceſſary for me in my deſerted condition, for want of leave; neither did His Highneſs recommend me to any other Patron; and I was neglected by my own Church, for which I had ſtudyed, and ſuffered all my days, and my Principles allowed me not to joyn with other Proteſtants, who more reſpected me for my Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrings and Integrity, though differing ever from them (for the wrongs of ſome mortal Governours of the church, was no exception or prejudice to me againſt the good Laws and Government it ſelf, as I anſwered ſome of them that invited me) neither was I to repair to my Living the Maſter-gin of my adverſaries, where old ſnares continued, and my <hi>Cow</hi> was milked, and ſubmiſſion was expected to unjuſt, ſcandalous, and-over ruled Cenſures, and their watch and frown upon my Converſe every where, made it difficult to live or breath, yet I was unwilling, for the reaſon at firſt, to cry out for help againſt my Fathers, or to make their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion known to the Nation for my relief and vindication.</p>
                  <p>Now I can diſcern no difference between being wounded by the hands of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, as Principals, or of Reverend Proteſtants (if for no other cauſe but Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancie) as Inſtruments, but that my Guard againſt Enemies in the ſhape of friends in Superioritie, was more difficult, and their Wounds pierced deeper by the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery and Indignity, and that the Maſter is to be rever'd above the Servant: nor how any other Clergie man in the ſame Circumſtances ſhould have eſcaped the ſame myſterious and unaccountable Danger and Trouble, if he had been as proud, and mad, as to prefer his Duty and Fidelity to his Church and Country, before his Worldly Intereſt and Advantage; ſurely from the beginning (of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation) it was not ſo New whether it be of publick Concern and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to prevent the like diſcouragement to others, from thoſe who ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encourage their Inferiors in ſuch Fidelity, I humbly leave it to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Judge.</p>
                  <p>Now I perceived that you well knew of this deſign and ſtorm againſt me, about two yeres before the Duke underſtood it, and I muſt ſay it to your Honour, that none of my adverſaries dealt more plainly with me, in fore telling both my dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and its cauſe, than you did, whereby I ſuſpect you could not be then igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this Popiſh Plot, in its firſt riſe and management.</p>
                  <p>For I remember, when upon Her late Highneſſes Her Order to me in 1664. to watch, and oppoſe the intollerable incroachments of the other Chappel at St. <hi>James,</hi> I had, amongſt other inſtances to check them, recommended <hi>D. M.</hi> in great diſtreſs and miſerie, to her Charitie and Protection, with much acceptance then, ſhe being a zealous Proteſtant in her own inclination; and he likewiſe under a good Charracter for Life and Birth, which the <hi>Portugal</hi> Chaplains (whom I was commanded to found) had nothing to except againſt; I did not find them ſo incenſ'd againſt him, and me, as I found you and your partie againſt us both, before any other Good, or Evil, was known of him, or objected againſt me.</p>
                  <p>For publiquely at Gentle-men-Waiters Table (among other moleſtations) you reproved me upon his ſcore, and were angry with him for changing his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and communicating with the <hi>French</hi> Church, (having then little or no En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh) and that the <hi>French</hi> and we differed not only in Dicipline but in Doctrine, and that you would keep him from your Sacrament at St. <hi>Jamſ</hi>'s if he offer'd to come there. And when I told you, the Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> did countenance him, and weekly relieved him with Her Highneſſes Charity, you aſſur'd me the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop was not for him, which afterwards appeared true to ſome purpoſe; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time, the ſame yere, before a private Sacrament, order'd Her Highneſs in Her cloſet by Her Confeſſor my Lord of <hi>Winton,</hi> for the recovery of the Duke
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63595:7"/>of <hi>Cambridge's</hi> health (which ſeemed a ſtrange uſe of a Proteſtant Sacrament to me) when I deſired to be in Charity with you, and to know the true cauſe of your diſpleaſure againſt me, with a purpoſe to give you Chriſtian ſatisfaction, you anſwered, that I had never done you any wrong, but that I ſhould be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the Family for unſound Principles, which I then deſired to know what they were, ſeeing <hi>I</hi> had been firm to the Church of England, before the Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and had no reaſon to deſert it ſince; but you would not then aſſign what they were, but you and your partie from that time, daily ſet your ſelves to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt me, and decry me, and diminiſh my Salary as afore, to diminiſh my Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, againſt contract with conſideration, and to exclude me from Preaching and officiating at all before the Dutches at St. <hi>Jamſ's.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For, beſides her <hi>monthly</hi> Sacrament days, (wherein ſhe remained at St. <hi>James's</hi>) you know, if you pleaſe, when it was my turn to Preach, ſhe began to ſtay the other Sundays, on which I was to Preach, at home to hear me, and not to goe to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and I remember, when ſhe found you were to Preach, when ſhe expected me, being as yet ignorant of the prohibition againſt my Preaching be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Her, She came not to Chappel, when you ſerved, but ſent for me from the Kings Chappel to read Prayers to Her in Her Cloſet, whereby I found She did not ſet on the Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> as he alledg'd, but was ſet on by him againſt me, which is of great uſe and importance to know, in order to find, by whom She was perverted.</p>
                  <p>And you ſtaid not here, but likwiſe prohibitted my Preaching and Officiating before the Duke at Sea, in his firiſt <hi>Dutch-War,</hi> and though I was the Chaplain appointed to attend him, and priviledg'd with a <hi>Cabbin,</hi> (which you knew to your ſorrow) and the Salary of the <hi>Ship,</hi> and at no other expedition had His Highneſs more than one Chaplain, yet as ſoon as I went to <hi>Sea,</hi> you were, as ſoon (after another that fell ſick) diſpatch'd after me, to make me a cipher, and to Officiate alone to His Highneſs all the while, and to Adminiſter Sacraments to him <hi>monthly</hi> in ſtead of Sermons, which were ſuppreſſed by my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> contrivance, againſt His Highneſs's firſt orders by His Almoner to me: and when I endeavour'd to have this order altered, (which was ſcandalous to the Fleet, and uncharitable to the Sea-mens needs, and desires) againſt my return after the fight to Sea, whither the Duke commanded me before him, with an intention to follow, this was the firſt and only colour and pretence of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that ever the Biſhop had, while I was at St. <hi>James's,</hi> to object againſt me, <hi>Bona fide</hi> and with any truth, whatever it were, though he began to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine me upon the ſcore of De <hi>Macedo</hi> about a yeare before: ſo that this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence (which the Duke was made to countenance) was like the Lambs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the River below ſtream, to the other Creature that drank above.</p>
                  <p>Among ſeveral paſſages at Sea, I could never forget one, which was, that if the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhould be then beaten, the neck of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> intereſt ſhould be broken; (and their deliverance then from being totally deſtroyed, I thought they owed not to Sleep or ſlackening Sails by night, as was rumoured, but to too much faith in men, and guides by day, in not falling on at an opportunity, as the Duke himſelf had a mind; a Providential pledge that Popery will be defeated by its own Principles.)</p>
                  <p>This ſtrange expreſſion (which reverence to the Government, made me then diſregard) I found afterwards too well to agree with paſſages in <hi>Coleman, Fitz-Harris,</hi> and Common's Addreſs, and the ſtrange alteration in <hi>France,</hi> againſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and when I asked you then, what Religion you were of, you ſaid you were of the Univerſal Church, and that <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> was a name of <hi>Schiſme:</hi> to which your prejudice I had a particular reſpect in my Booke, leaſt His Highneſs had imbib'd the ſame from you, or your party, as ſometimes the patient is to be Adminiſtred unto, through the Nurſe.</p>
                  <p>Now I hear'd, and you better know, I am ſure, that there was a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prieſt in the Ship, But, if there was another in a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> mask, to celebrate <hi>Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi> Sacraments, with a deſign'd malice the ſame time againſt the very throat of <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> the diſſimulation of our Tyburn <hi>Jeſuites</hi> comes ſhort of this, in ſome reſpects: but it could never ſink into my ſuſpition and belief, how any ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Perſon of clear Honour, and Courage, or of underſtanding as to know and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63595:7"/>recognize the right Soveraign of his heart, could be won, or bewitched by any damnable diſpenſation, to diſſemble with God and man, on Deaths borders, for any Worldly deſign or end. And if <hi>Preteſtants</hi> have been out-witted to maſſacre and ruine one another by colliſion of their vaſt force and treaſure, yet Heaven appeard remarkably againſt it, to hinder and part them, by miraculous miſts, and an unparalel'd Plague and Fire, in which laſt permitted judgment the ſubſervient malice of <hi>Rome</hi> viſibly croſſed its own deſigns, and ſuffered <hi>Amſterdam</hi> to eſcape for once, to purſue a ſtudied opportunity (never elſe to be regained) of retor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, 666. on <hi>London,</hi> And if this be ſo, The Lord in mercy watch over this poor Nation, our Cities, Fleet, Univerſities, Libraries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And teach our Senators Wiſdom, and <hi>deliver me and</hi> (others) <hi>from Blood guiltneſs O God, thou God of my Salvation, and my tongue ſhall ſing aloud of thy Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pſal. 51.</p>
                  <p>The Even before the fight, <hi>June</hi> 2.65. when both Fleets were neare together, I was commanded (becauſe you were unwilling) to Officiate and exhort, (which I did with <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſincerity) and with what an acknowledg'd omen of victory, annnex'd to the duty, you may perhaps remember, for you among others told me then of his Highneſs's beliefe, declard to that purpoſe: but neither the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of Heaven believed, nor intenſe Favour by other laudable means ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd, and Graciouſly atteſted to his Majeſty, and the World; nor falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations baffled and confuted, and innocency fully cleared, nor the undoubted Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right and charge, and glory of Rulers to puniſh knaves rather than honeſt men, (which I did humbly intimate and inſiſt on) could ſecure me from being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in a moment (and that as ſoon as I was newly delivered from the ſame publick dangers) according to your infallible prediction as afore, now ſeconded with other <hi>Popiſh</hi> threats, both <hi>Forraign</hi> and <hi>Domeſtick</hi> about the time of De. <hi>Macedo's</hi> miraculous eſcape at <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> and his appearing to me at St. <hi>James's</hi> after he had been burnt for <hi>Sodomy</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> about half a yere before, (as ſome of your party publickly affirmed to my face) and complaining of a conſpiracy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſome of your party, and the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Chaplains againſt his life, made very probable to me, by other good Teſtimonies, and Cadaverous faces, and Gentile tricks, and Parliaments from this time awakened to enquire into the inſolence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Popery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now though I can, and daily have prayed, that God would forgive your wrongs to me, yet I am not to forgive your wrongs to my Friends, eſpecially to the Duke and Nation; nor the cauſe and root of this general diſturbance to all manner of People, and of the high and unheard of debates between Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, and <hi>Salus publica,</hi> and care of the Kings Life, and of our Laws, and Liberties, and Religion, leaſt they become Articles of <hi>Nants</hi> (for to uſe the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expired right and duty of a Chaplain) I take them to be the firſt Authors of the doleful bill of excluſion, who for preferments, have at firſt complyed, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd to thoſe revolts, that work the (once darling Prince) out of the hearts and truſts of the People, to the great infelicitie of both. Whereby the Nation is nigh diſſolved in fiction, as in a ſeparation of Soul and Body, for what is a Nation, though never formidable and renoun'd, without a Prince, they can truſt, but a dead unactive Carcaſs? or what is a Prince, though never ſo magnanimous, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the hearts and truſts of his People, but a lean wandering Ghoſt and Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
                  <p>An army without a general, or a general without an Army, ſignified the ſame in <hi>Caeſars,</hi> as <hi>a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf,</hi> in our Saviours account, but the Blind man in the fable, that could go, taking the cripple upon his back, that could ſee, enabled both to ſee and walk. And ſome States-men deſcribe the <hi>vnlgus</hi> or part ruled, to be as a blind Creature, that cannot ſee, but feel; the reſignation of its ſight, being its truſt and ſubmiſſion; the retention of its feeling, its right and cuſtome to taſte and judge, whether it were righted or betrayed, whether it truſted Gods or Devils: for never was their Genuine unrepentable truſt, but in order to be holpe and defended by another, as a God. <hi>And Gods part is truly act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all thoſe, that count it Divine Honour, dearer than life it ſelf, to be true in trust. Now the infinite God himſelf, the King of Kings, and true meaſure of all right Governing, (if it could be imagin'd his Creatures could expect nought but ſham's and ſnares, and deſtruction, from him) could never gain their truſt, which is eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63595:8"/>correlate to Truth and Love; upon which ſcore, ſome aſſertions about abſolute Decrees, and Reprobation, are ſuſpected as unſound, becauſe known to lead to deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and to take off the truſt of the Soul.</hi> Our <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> likewiſe, though the beſt of Chriſtians and Subjects, (with ſome) would hardly truſt a <hi>Luther</hi> to be their <hi>Pope,</hi> or an <hi>Hugenot</hi> to be their King, though a right Heir. And there are the ſame Natural inſtincts, to preſerve themſelves and their poſterities, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, preliminary to all other ties: and the Church of <hi>England</hi> is too unkindly requited, to be ſlighted and abandoned as <hi>Heretical,</hi> and <hi>Carnal,</hi> which hath num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of her Sons of a more ſublime and Primitive-like Loyalty, who think it Conſcience to forget the Engliſh-man, to make good the Chriſtian, as if their ſeveral rights and intereſts were inconſiſtent, or, as if <hi>Magna-Charta</hi> and our other good Laws, (which are conceived to be in danger by this revolt) were not <hi>Juris divini</hi> in ſome ſenſe, and confirmed by the <hi>13th.</hi> to the <hi>Romans, Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> ſuch Statutes being undoubtedly the deliberate, and moſt certain and ſolemn Will and Declaration, of the Supream Powers in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, which the Apoſtolical Injunction requires all due obedience to (being our true Loyalty according to the true ſenſe and etymology of the word) upon the peril of Damnation as well as Treaſon: inſomuch that many ſuſpect, and object, it muſt be preferment; or the belly, and not Conſcience, that ſways, where the Divine will is ſo neglected, and the Heaven that is preferr'd before Earth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Laws and Liberties of their Country, by a counterfeit Zeal and Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is their own Paramount Private ends, and phancied accommodations and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and advancement, being a ſort of Luſt and diſorder (in exhalting a part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole, againſt Law and Conſcience) that Tyburn and Hell, were erected and conſtituted, to correct and puniſh the like Principle in the general, in every Malèfactor, and Sinner, that ever did, or ſhall ſuffer in, or on them: on the like inducements, the ſingle will and pleaſure of an old crazie Pope ſeduced by luſts and flatteries, finds more votaries and voices at <hi>Rome</hi> (ſuch as they be) for its infallible Authority, than their general Councils can, which ſeldome meete, and beſtow fewer promotions, though both Popes themſelves, and their <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, and God himſelf are acknowledg'd by them to be preſent in the latter, without diſpute.</p>
                  <p>Beſides the Pope himſelf (who muſt needs ſmile to himſelf, at mens devout preference of his Quacke-intereſt before the good of their own Country) was more faithful and careful of His Highneſs's ſafety, when he adviſed him to be wary in declaring, as knowing perhaps the Divine and Noble conſtitution of this Realm, which knows no error in the Crown, ſpares no treaſon in the Subject. Therefore the Commitment of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, when Prince, is recorded in our Hiſtories, without cenſure, yea with the eulogy of the King his Father, for the courage and impartiality of his Courts, and the ſubmiſſion of his Son. The Laws interpoſing and revengeing all wrong, and violation, by any Creature, or Subject, either unto the Divine State and Prerogative, and Perſon of the King (who anſwers to the hallowed deity <hi>Above</hi>) or againſt the cognate ſafety of the publick, (which is, as the whole to the part, <hi>Below,</hi> or as end to means, or God to Creature) the King, Laws, and publick ſafety (if I rightly underſtand the Government, I am bound to obey and preſerve) theſe three with us, being as one, and none but State <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Traytors</hi> deny this Trinity, or divide this Unity.</p>
                  <p>But neither His Holyneſs, nor your party, were true to his Highneſs's Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Conſcience, in allowing him to act ſecretly, againſt the Religion he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd openly, before he had as openly renounc'd it. For <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves, (if the caſe were againſt themſelves) would abhor ſuch prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices by the mere light of Nature, which is the reaſon that by the Laws of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, broad ſides at Sea are never given under falſe Coulours: and was the direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion clear and Engliſh-like, to be given or followed, to entertain a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Chaplain into ſervice, to be ruin'd for his honeſty, and openneſs in his Profeſſion, by ſecret underboard Arts? (which I mention not for private concern, but for the certainty of the inſtance) what will be thought of them that fared better by their prudence and flexibility? or thoſe ſpecially, who were active inſtruments in ſuch deſigns againſt one of their own Coat and Profeſſion?</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:63595:8"/>
                  <p>But in nothing is this change and revolt from all truth and goodneſs, more pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably unnatural and irreligious, than that it wounded the Glorious Fathers Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor in his grave, making him acceſſary to what he did forbid, and much juſtifying the Fears and Calumnies of his Enemies, and flurring the cauſe of his ſuffering friends: and caſts his only Brother and Soveraign, that ſtands in the way, into a manifeſt and daily Jeopardy of his Life, by inevitable conſequence, from the known practiſes and principles of <hi>Rome,</hi> though no actual Plot, or deſign to aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinat his Royal Perſon had been proved, or believed: And which is as unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant as death it ſelf, diſturbs his dayes with a moſt ungrateful dilemma, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, of loving a Brother before the Community, or the Community before a Brother, when neither part can be choſen without a great and general diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, or unkindneſs: All which inconvenience had been eaſily prevented by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in his bleſſed Fathers Religion, (wherein none of your party were ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned for their councils) and I truſt, might be ſtill redreſſed by his return to the Truth, to be our bleſſing, in the manner <hi>I</hi> humbly deſcribed in a Letter to <hi>Edenburrough</hi> in <hi>June</hi> laſt, and in another to Sir <hi>A. A.</hi> ſome while before, and inſinuated alſo as much in 1677. in my Dedicatory Epiſtle to His Highneſs himſelf.</p>
                  <p>For ſure the Nation and City in General deſign no hurt to the Duke, to a haire of his head, or line of his Picture, but have very ſtrong deſires to be effectually ſafe in their deareſt concerns from the ſworn Enemies of their Religion and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, too much hearkned to: I know a perſon that was torn, and like to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a tame and generous Maſtiff, when a little Childe, for dallying too long and withholding his bit from him when he was hungry; I know no greater Enemies to the Duke, than your ſervile parasfitical party who by Loyal complyance with all his feavoriſh appetites, for their advantage, have betrayed him into this diſeaſe, and perplexity, and danger, and ſtrange revenge, not againſt Enemies, but beſt friends, and the Glory of his Fathers memory, by loading it with an odious and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious new diſcovery of a probable cauſe of his ſad difaſter permitted by providence (which overrules the Malice of Men and Devils to this Glorious ends) while all will eaſily ſee and judge that the Revolt of the Son (the ſorrow and trouble of all good men, the open boaſt and ſhelter of Papiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Secret joy and mockery of Republicans) was the likely effect of his unequal marriage, and the Blood and Maſſacre and confuſion, that is feared, the likely effect of this revolte. All foreſeen, and diſliked by the omniſcient Wiſdom, which chaſteneth in whom it loveth, any root, or cauſe of miſcheif, there being beſides a particular Remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble providence over this Iſle, which makes kind Aſpects towards Popery inauſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to our <hi>Britiſh</hi> Crown, and an effectual ſincere Zeal to ſuppreſs it, Fortunate and Glorious to our Princes, as <hi>I</hi> offer to conſideration, <hi>pag.</hi> 373. Hearts Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</p>
                  <p>But the truth is, when <hi>I</hi> was well fitted by His Highneſs's extraordinary Favour and good opinion (as is well known to all about then him) to direct, or retard him, by love, or argument, or ſupplications, from ſuch hazardous and degenerate moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (upon miſtaken Zeal) againſt our Church, and Kingdom, and Himſelf, in all his Intereſts, Temporal, Moral, and Eternal, and to recommend to him the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to be gloriouſly uſeful and dear to <hi>GOD</hi> and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try (as I do in my Book) or of Queen <hi>Chriſtina</hi> to merit a Heaven and kinde tribute by being civil, (which I leave to others to adviſe:) How did your party never reſt, to hazard their Honour and Salvation, by multiplying falſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, to remove ſuch Lumber from about His Highneſs: though I obſerved none of the Bed-Chamber that joyned in this Intrigue againſt me but only one, Sir <hi>A. A.</hi> but rather of their own accord did intercede often for me; nor indeed any within, or without the Houſe, but the Relations, and Creatures, and Subcreatures of an unfortunat Grandee, then in very great Power, and your old P. if <hi>I</hi> well remember. Could any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man or Chriſtian refrain to oppoſe, or teſtify to his power againſt ſuch wrongs and abuſes to his Prince and Nation from bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Friends? <hi>Seek the Peace of the City,</hi> faith the Prophet, <hi>and pray unto the Lord for it, for in the peace thereof ye ſhall have peace,</hi> Jer. 27.7.</p>
                  <p>Therefore in 1668. after the remove of the Lord Chancelor <hi>H.</hi> (the head of your party and deſigne, upon the ſcore of matches, as I imagined and felt) I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63595:9"/>applyed my ſelf upon a juſt occaſion to ſome Reverend Biſhops, met near my Pariſh, to deſire their aſſiſtance to have this matter ſearched and examined, leaſt there were a Plot laid againſt this Church, hoping by the ſounder part to detect, and work out the more unſound, with leſs ſcandal and danger then by any other method I could uſe, or think of; but inſtead of being holpe or directed, I was oppreſſed, and betrayed, and inſtead of being produced a witneſs for the Publick, made a defendant to an action of <hi>Scandalum magnatum,</hi> by wilful miſconſtruction of my diſcourſe, againſt a paper to the contrary leſt with them under my hand, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed on, which they concealed from that time to this: the coppy whereof can be produced.</p>
                  <p>And in <hi>December</hi> 1678. after the breaking out of this Popiſh Plot, In obedience to his Majeſties Proclamations, I communicated what light I could thereunto by a a-breviate of my ſufferings and for what cauſe, delivered to an Honorable, and fit Perſon of the Privy-Council, but nothing was made thereof, nor I enquired af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any more. Only I obſerved an unexpected retrograd motion (like a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the dead) from <hi>Farnham</hi> to <hi>London</hi> thereupon, to joyn with other great Biſhops to recover the Duke to the Church, or perhaps to cover one of their number from contrary ſuſpition, by a kind abſolution, of which boaſt hath been made, but what ever was the deſign, the event of the meeting, as I heard, was to let the World ſee, that his Highneſs neither was, nor would be directed by the Biſhops; in ſome contrariety, and check to his laſt anſwer to me, as afore, wherewith I was cruſhed and tantalized, by their directions, for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years: ſo much their care was more for ſome of their own ſafeties, then of His Highneſs's honour; but I obſerved no ſuch diſpleaſure againſt <hi>them</hi> for ſhutting the Stable door ſo late, as from His Highneſs, and one of them againſt me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, for giving the alarme and warning, before the Steed was gone.</p>
                  <p>By all I have nothing to boaſt, but that I have made good my innocence, and Loyal integrity againſt all exceptions and colours whatſoever; and neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, nor protection, nor juſtice, nor equity, nor mercy, nor truth, nor any plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealing have been made good (ſave only from your ſelf) unto me, to this day, and I have <hi>Overcome Evil with Good, and have not been overcome by it, to GOD I give the Praiſe.</hi> Such being the harmleſs victory of Martyrs over Heatheniſh Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> notes, <hi>Non ceſſiſſe, viciſſe eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now the moſt open publication of this dark Myſtery, to the conſideration of Authority, and the World is ſufficiently ſafe and ſeaſonable, and neceſſary: the whole Nation being now known to it ſelf, to be entirely united and reſolved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popery, in which point, both Addreſſers and Excluders, and his Majeſty, all agree, and the danger of Fanatical Confuſion and Sacriledge, and ſtriking at the Antient Order for the faults of Perſons, litle feared: or the like defect and danger better to be rectified, and remedied another way, without wrong to the King and Publick Councils, or wound and ſcandal to Religion.</p>
                  <p>So that your maſquerad party appear very ſmall and contemptible, and miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and eaſily to be blown off to publick Satifaction: who while undiſcerned and unremoved, were for divers years very conſiderable, by their neerneſs to vitals, &amp; great influence and power, eſpecially over the Clergy and Univerſities to help, or hurt, or corrupt, or (as in my caſe,) to vex and oppreſs to death, by a new colour and myſtery of a through-paced obedience required to ſuperiours, right or wrong, and leading, the Lord knowes whither, as in a ſtring, (contrary to the Tenor of Canonical Oaths, which bind only to things lawful and juſt) enough to put in mind of the Plot in <hi>Sparta,</hi> where the Guards were ſtrictly charged to obey their Chief Officer in all things whatſoever, while he himſelf had ſecret Inſtructions to kill and new mould the Government.</p>
                  <p>So that and effectual convictive diſcovery of the remainder of your party would be of more uſe to unite and eſtabliſh this Nation perhaps, than the hanging of 1000. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits,</hi> which could not do us half that hurt without, as they within, and none better fitted for ſuch a diſcovery then your ſelf, (and ſome others whom I can name) as any may gather from your early and infallible prediction of my ruine, long before the Duke did know, or conſent thereto: And conſpiracies of this nature againſt our Church, are better diſcovered by Actors in them, then ſufferers by them, the one evidence to the other being but as a Coppy to the Original,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63595:9"/>though yet not altogether uſeleſs, in the detection of ſuch dark deſignes.</p>
                  <p>All this in ſhort, Reverend Sir, is humbly and truly, to repreſent, what faithful Guides and Directors, the Chief of your party have been to his Highneſs, as to his Honour, and Concience, and intereſt in this Proteſtant Nation; And to exhort and moniſh you, (as <hi>I</hi> have done others) to become a diſcoverer of the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical part of this Popiſh Plot, or (if you will not) to leave it to the Publick, to Judge of us both, as to the diſcharge of our ſeveral duties. The Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> bind you to make your beſt diſcovery; And the Nation would be glad of a Grave and unexceptionable evidence at this juncture (if you have a heart to ſerve your Nation) you are bound thereto, for ſafety as well as duty, and for fear as well as conſcience; for if you are a Proteſtant, you ought not to deny it, or if a Papiſt, not to be tollerated in ſuch a place and charge. <hi>It</hi> cannot be thought that <hi>I</hi> write all this now for private advantage or ſplean, but rather out of conſcience and duty to the Publick, before <hi>I</hi> dye, becauſe your whole party are not able to make me ſufficient reparation for what <hi>I</hi> have ſuffered theſe <hi>ſixteen</hi> or <hi>eighteen</hi> Years together in my calling, and credit, and fortunes, and peace, and time, and loſs of the Dukes ſpecial Favour, and wrong of next Orphan relations, and haſten'd deaths of others, but <hi>I</hi> verily believe, that ſome of the chiefeſt of your party have been beholding many years to my patience and tenderneſs for the Duke and the Church, to the neglect of my own opportunities, and intereſt, and relief.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>
                        <hi>Sir,</hi> You had a right to this freedom for ſeveral reſpects, from,</salute> 
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your humble Servant, <hi>Thomas Iones.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>February,</hi> 22. 1681.</date> 
                        <hi>Kingſtreet,</hi> &amp;c.</dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>A Letter ſent to SCOTLAND, To the Reverend Dr. <hi>Turner,</hi> His Royal Highneſs Chaplain at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending his Houſhould in <hi>Edenburgh.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>TO none it is better known perhaps, then to you, how, and for what cauſe for many years together, I have had my fortunes wholy ruined, my good name wounded, my calling diſturbed, my converſe ſtreightened, my ſences queſtioned, and my truth and teſtimony at laſt, attempted to be wreſted from me, by Importunities and Curſes, by Power and Fraud, by great Offers, and long Streits and Seidge, but in vain, and without effect, this laſt poſſeſſion being more within my power.</p>
                  <p>And I have ſurvived, I bleſs God to ſee (as the reward and victory of Truth and Patience, the proper trophee becoming our calling) all my Enemies from the greateſt to your ſelf, baſted and condemned in all their pretences and Reproaches, not only before God and their own conſciences, and my knowledge, as ever, but alſo, at laſt before the World, by detection of Plots, and deciſions of providence, and voluntary confeſſions, in parties penitent; and ſhameful retreats and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, and checkmates, in contrary diſpoſitions, as will appear in the enſuing Narrative:</p>
                  <p>And as to you, by your preſent Imployment at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> which is not to Read Maſs in the Cloſet, I ſuppoſe, but to ſerve the Family, wherein you are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63595:10"/>become my ſucceſſor, as well as Drs. <hi>Doughty,</hi> and <hi>Lake</hi> by Land, and <hi>Woodroff</hi> by Sea: and yet time was, that I was to be no Chaplain for it, but to be ſhun'd and diſown'd by you, and your party, and hindered to Chatechiſe, or to Preach before the Ducheſs at St. <hi>James,</hi> or to the Duke at Sea, and to have my Salary diminiſhed, and withheld from me, in that part, and more, to this day, with many other unſchollar-like and barbarous paſſages, not Inferior to Infamous Cravats, to weary me out of the Family, and my Life, for no Cauſe in the World, but for appearing early againſt Popery, at St. <hi>Jame's,</hi> and Introduceing De <hi>Macedo,</hi> and being a probable and likely Inſtrument perhaps (by a paſſionate favour and good opinion) of preſerving His Highneſs in His Fathers Religion, and endevouring at laſt to bring this Plot to Light in. 1668.</p>
                  <p>This Preface therefore I judged fit to direct to you afore hand, who have ſo Zealouſly concern'd your ſelf in moſt part of this Tragedy (in obedience to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours I ſuppoſe) either to awaken your Lethargick conſcience, better to mind the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, which enjoyns upon the peril of perjury to diſcloſe conſpiracies of this nature, as well for our own as the Nations ſafety; and I doubt not but you can poſitively prove by hearing and ſeeing what I can moſtly prove by ſufferring: for I obſerv'd you, and your party, to foretell aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly my ruine, when the Duke was ignorant of the delign, and fully reſolv'd againſt it; and you will be truer alſo to the Church, and the Duke (whoſe bread you eat) as well as to your conſcience, by diſcovering thoſe falſe guids, who either by direct Influence, or Obediential Paraſitical compliance, and deſtruction of faithful obſtructors, have encourag'd his Gracious Highneſs, in deſigns, ſo diſturbing and hazardous to himſelf and <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks, as well as to the whole nation.</p>
                  <p>Or, if I fail herein, to warn the Nation further, as my laſt part, to read in my ſufferings their own great danger from Maſquerade <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and a few diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſ'd Woolves got within the Sheepfold, more hurtful and pernicious, than hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of <hi>Whitebreads</hi> and <hi>Hartcourts</hi> from without; for if an approv'd ſervant, and companion of dangers, and alwayes Epiſcopal, and Loyal, have been ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely and courſly uſed for <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> by their means, profeſſing themſelves as yet the ſame Religion, what muſt other more unrighteous and ſtuborn Hereticks throughout the Nation, in proper time expect?</p>
                  <p>And though I have been ſufficiently haraſ'd, by prevalent unprovoked Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries (with the help of my own truſt and reverence towards them) yet I ſhall not yield my ſelf fully conquer'd, till I am beaten out of my Principles, and faith to King and Nation, as well as out of my accommodations; and therefore out of invict duty and fidelity ſhall not fear to add,</p>
                  <p>That if Popery, and ſlavery, be more deſirable than publick Peace and Crowns, it will yet be more Princely and Generous to come to our Church once more, and diſcover, for publick ſatisfaction and reparation, thoſe treacherous carnal guides, who for a preſent preferment, betrayed a ſincere and pious Prince, through ſuch diſguiſe, to hurt himſelf, and friends, before declaration; elſe how can it be ſaid, that he ſuffers, as a Chriſtian, or a <hi>Catholick</hi> for a true, but rather for the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy fruits, and dangerous malignity of a falſe Religion: neither will this be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable or difficult; for Princes who have a right to the utmoſt fidelity of all men, may with greater honour and glory, before God and man, Sacrifice Knaves for treachery, than honeſt men for truth: and then turn <hi>Papiſt</hi> again, to our ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and ſpate not, but with Engliſh valour, and fair warning; and He turn <hi>Papiſt</hi> too, though none others will; and renegue this ancient and Apoſtolical Mother-Church, and all her Rights, provided any principle in my Prefaces, or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in my ſmall Book, can be unſetled; till then, for better, for worſe, I ſhall through Gods Grace, continue,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Proteſtant Servant, <hi>Thomas Iones.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>June</hi> 18. 1681.</date> 
                        <hi>Kingſtreet,</hi> &amp;c.</dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THis Letter had prefixed before it, a Preface to my intended Memorial for the Diſcovery of Maſquerad Proteſtants, with the Text, <hi>Judg.</hi> 19, 30. but the Town being full of News from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> thereupon, that His Highneſs did intend to return to our Church, I forbore farther thoughts thereof for ſome time.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63595:10"/>
                  <head>A Letter to Sir <hi>A. A.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I am well informed, that you were lately pleaſ'd to traduce me to D. <hi>O.</hi> a publick Perſon, beſtowing hard characters upon me unworthy of your ſelf or me, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The ground and provocation I find, was, for demanding of my own, whereof I ſent you the ſtate and account, at Mr. <hi>Swifts</hi> deſire, and amply proved the Dukes will and order for payment thereof, to D. <hi>O.</hi> his ſatisfaction againſt your mean ſugeſtions, whereby there is owing to me about or 1.</p>
                  <p>You give me occaſion hereby to recollect how privy and inſtrumental you were in an early Aſſaſination I endur'd from great tongues in 1666. at St. <hi>James's,</hi> for no cauſe, but Proteſtancy, and that under the covert of a friend, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt contempt of the Dukes declar'd kindneſs and frequent defences, which was not very Mannerly nor Loyal, nor ſafe perhaps in you, or your party (as ſome would have though) but that you well underſtood your grounds, and that occult inclination which would enſure you, when you moſt thwarted his Royal Will and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: for others of the Bed-Chamber, as much ſtrangers to me, as your ſelf, who diſcern'd not then this <hi>Catholick</hi> byas, could not forbear to mind His Highneſs free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it was not for His Highneſs's Honour to deſtroy his innocent ſervant, who ſtood to him in his dangers, and himſelf had publickly commended.</p>
                  <p>Whether or no you likewiſe forgot the Oath of Allegiance, &amp;c. and concealed thoſe Perſons, that then, or ſince, perverted their Royal Highneſſes traiterouſly from the Church (as well as treacherouſly from me) will then beſt appear, when this matter, ſo much tending to diſcover the Root and bottom of this Helliſh Plot (which ſome would make a Fable for their Security) ſhall by Authority be throughly ſearched, in proper time.</p>
                  <p>Its a ſatisfaction to me above all preferment, or Salary, that I preferred my fidelity to His Royal Highneſs Honour, and Conſcience, and Intereſt in theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Nations, in times of tryall, though ruined for it in barbarous manner: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I envy, or dread the deſpicable felicity and grandeur of any of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary complyance, and ſucceſs. How ſoon will this proſperity be Sowred, If God (who can do it in an inſtant to the great joy of Prince and People) ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline his Highneſs heart, to be more guided by the Laws and Councils of this Nation, then by forreign Cheats, or Domeſtick Slaves and Paraſites, and to do as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius Chlorus</hi> did at <hi>York,</hi> to ſuch his Servants, as denyed Chriſt to pleaſe the Emperour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sir,</hi> though I forgive your calumnies, yet Ile make bold humbly to mind your conſcience to think of Reparations to the publick.</p>
                  <p>And likewiſe not to wrong His R. Highneſs's Juſtice and Honour, in witholding my due Salary any longer from me, for I am no gainer by the Dukes Service, or his living <hi>(in Wales.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some of your penitent Brethren, in the ſame intrigue, have gone further, as to make ſome Chriſtian acknowledgments of the many wrongs, they with you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, have done to,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Honourable</hi> Sir. <hi>Your,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>July.</hi> 7. 1680.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>A Letter to Sir <hi>J. W.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HAving reſolved to adhear ever to my Duty, and fidelity to His Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Publick, whatever were my tryals, or deſertion; in purſuance of the ſame Loyal Fidelity, I have preſumed in this method through you, being diſcouraged in all other addreſſes, humbly to requeſt his Royal Highneſs to peruſe and conſider a ſhort explicit Letter of concern and moment lately writ on a juſt occaſion to Sir. <hi>A. A.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>From his long oppreſſed Servant, <hi>Thomas Iones,</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <date>
                        <hi>July,</hi> 21. 1680.</date>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:63595:11"/>
                  <head>To His Royal Highneſs, JAMES Duke of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Albany,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your Royal Highneſs,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AS the Peace of Kingdoms,<note place="margin">My Epiſtle Dedicatory to His R. H. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered with my Book of the <hi>Hearts Right Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> into His R. H. Hands at St. James's Oct. 31. 1677</note> which your Royal Highneſs excellently knows, and the duty and ſafety of Subjects, together with the great eaſe of Princes, conſiſt in one ſhort, eaſie rule, and equitable, well maintaind, and practiced, The ſubmiſſion of the Creature to its Creator; or the Obedience of Inferiours, in the low condition of the one, to their reſpective Superiours over them, in the Authority, and high Character of the other; ſo it may be affirm'd, that the Peace and welfare of the Church depends no leſs upon the like leſſon and method.</p>
                  <p>For what are Conventicles, Schiſmes, Hereſies, Idolatries, which diſturbe the Peace, and deſtroy the being of the one; but like ſo many Riots, Factions, Seditions, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which alike undermine, and overthrow the Conſtitution of the other? ſo that in ſhort, the Diſturbers of the World, are thoſe alone, who diſobey Superiours.</p>
                  <p>Who, in the time, and under the Covert, of Peace, are of two ſorts; ſuch as unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deſpiſe the <hi>Right,</hi> or treacheroſly erect a <hi>Wrong</hi> Soveraign over themſelves. The firſt are thoſe, who from Avarice, or Pride, or Ambition, by craft or force, diſobey the Laws, and uſurp and encroach upon the Rights, and Prerogatives of their lawful Governours; where every inconſiderable Inceptor, and Puny Recuſant, is a <hi>Cromwel,</hi> or <hi>Luciſer,</hi> in his Path and tendency. The next thoſe, who through fear, or eaſineſs, will admit, or ſubmit, to any wrong pretender in his uſurpations, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Serpent againſt God: And then it cannot be expected, but that they, who miſtake their Sovereign in the firſt place, will miſtake their Loyalty in the next; And Allegiance miſplac'd ſhall make men Rebels, as much as the failer or ſubduction. The prime indiſpenſable charge thereof, firſt of Heaven's King, next of every King on Earth that repreſent him, is that known Commandment; <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Peace therefore of Churches and States manifeſtly conſiſts in two points. <hi>1.</hi> In the exact knowledge and diſcovery, who are our <hi>Right,</hi> and lawful Superiou s on Earth. <hi>2.</hi> In exact obedience performed to their Laws and Will, and no other. Nor to <hi>Them,</hi> acting beyond their Sphere, and uſurping upon <hi>Gods</hi> Rights in Heaven, under whom all Eartly Superiours and Inferiours are <hi>Equally</hi> Fellow ſubjects. And not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the liberty of eyes, and underſtanding, or private judgment, to diſcerne between right or wrong Leaders, which is of ſuch temporal concern and preſervation to every man in this World; nor between the will of God, and his Creature, where they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere, which is of ſuch Eternal moment in the other, (wherein lies the Radical errour of ſome <hi>Modern Chriſtian Heatheniſm</hi>) were to be depos'd from being men any more, or reduced to an Eternal <hi>Non-age</hi> and inability, to diſcern between good and evil, and fitter therefore to be governed, than to govern either themſelves, or others.</p>
                  <p>Having therefore, for the eſtabliſhment of Friends, and the comfort of Regular, and recovery of Irregular, and ſeduc'd ſufferers for Religion, beſtowed endeavours, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the ſeveral parts of Divine and Human Soverainty, whereon the Peace of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, and the Salvation of Souls depends, (being as manifeſtly diſtinguiſhable, as Heaven and Earth, or Soul and Body,) and ſtated alſo, and evinced the Title of <hi>Right Mother-Church,</hi> to our own <hi>Britain;</hi> (though its known, a Harlot can bid fair for a true Mother, where ſhe lights not on <hi>Solomons</hi> for Judges, and where ſhe does, be willing the Child be divided into Sects, and parcels, which ſhe is not like to enjoy to her ſelf entire,) and ſufficiently demonſtrated, (to any whoſe invincible minds and Spirits are unreduced from their Loyalty to God and Truth,) That Popery, in its Leaders, is an uniform in invaſion, and in its followers, a neceſſary diſobedience to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63595:11"/>right Soveraignes, in Heaven and Earth, and Proteſtancy in its Principles to be ſafe and clear from ſuch diſorders;</p>
                  <p>I judged fit to dedicate the Argument, to whom it was duty to preſent the firſt Copy, to your Royal Highneſs, my Gracious Prince, and Maſter, having afore-hand weighed and conſidered, (as I ought,) it would make for your Highneſs Honour, and publick love, either at <hi>Home,</hi> or <hi>Abroad,</hi> in the disjunctive, whatever were its reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or ſucceſs: At <hi>Home,</hi> with God and the Country, if it ſerv'd in the leaſt to fortifie your Royal Breaſt againſt temptations, or at leaſt with <hi>Forreign</hi> Lords of Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Crowns, and <hi>Canonizations, if it fayl'd; againſt whoſe Sacred Avarice, and Catholick canting, for Tribute and Subjection, and other Politick Arts, which are not unknown, and infallible errours and Idolatries, which are not unconfuted, ſuch plain and manifeſt Truth could ſo little prevail; though from clean hands and ends, and ſeconded,</hi> with the ſenſe of the whole Nation, and the rights of this Ancient <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Church, undoubtedly <hi>Senior,</hi> if not <hi>Mother</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Withal, the Subject being of the <hi>Heart,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and comprizing, as the <hi>heart</hi> doth, in a narrow Rome, a competent ſtock of Divine Rules, and Meaſure, to judge of Truth, (and about Church matters) ſeem'd therefore the fitter preſent for a Prince, ſo nigh to Soveraign, who is a nation contracted in one man.</p>
                  <p>And Princes, like God whom they repreſent, delight in <hi>hearts:</hi> And no Prince in Story was ever the <hi>Darling,</hi> of more <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hearts, than your <hi>R. H.</hi> and ſtrange and unjuſt it were, you ſhould ſuffer any abatement of that Glory, for no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but your exalted ſuperlative zeal for God, and your Conſcience, above Crowns, or Kingdoms, being the higheſt ſtreign and pitch of ſublime and tranſcendant Honour, that Mortality could ever exert or phancy; and higher ſtill, if that zeal were well guided with deſcretion, (as the Apoſtle requires,) and not taken upon undue truſt; whereof if there were not ſome manifest cauſe to doubt, or fear, none were more inexcuſable, and worthy to be deſerted for ever by Your <hi>R. H.</hi> than him, who having had once the Honour, to adhere to you in your military dangers, ſhould want a <hi>heart</hi> at laſt to follow you in your Excleſiaſtical motions after truth, my proper Element and Profeſſion.</p>
                  <p>Having therefore, as I ought, doubted my ſelf not a little, and reviewed my Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples upon this occaſion, and with beſt endeavours of Brain and Knee, ſtudied to know the Truth, and God's Mind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, with a <hi>heart</hi> reſolved to be of its ſide, to my Power, againſt the World, it ſeemed agreeable to Miniſterial Obligation, as well as Loyal Reputation, to communicate my ſatisfactions to the World, in the view of your <hi>R. H.</hi> that all might ſee that nothing elſe was able to make a Loyal <hi>Britain</hi> ſhrink from the ſteps of his Prince but a greater Loyalty to the manifeſt rights of God, and the King, and the Truth.</p>
                  <p>Which I truſt, will not be conſtrued Contempt, but conſtancy, nothing being more the Duty of every Loyal ſervant, (and a Minister eſpecially) than to be as faithful to his Prince, (and conſequently to God and the Nation,) as Conſcience is in every breaſt, which will never approve, or agree to any diſloyal revolt from Heaven and Truth, but will chuſe rather to be ſilenc'd for a time than conſent, and with Patient agony refer the matter to God himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Nor are any to be reckon'd ſtraight-way unfortunate (as is the manner of ſome Weak and Carnal reaſons, and <hi>Turba Remi,</hi> and alſo the Divinity of ſome grave Deacons of the belly, and preſent eaſe and greatneſs,) for any wound, or inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, they may bring upon themſelves, for ſuch fidelity to the Temporal and Eternal Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of their Maſter, either from declar'd, which is more fair, or undeclar'd, and inviſible Hoſtilities, which is leſs: For ſuch ſuffer in their manifeſt <hi>duties,</hi> which is therefore to be preſum'd to be their <hi>choice</hi> by conſequence, (when ſuch need require) and their right, and beſt ſelf-preſervation, (if they be right men and Chriſtians,) for if we are bound to love our Neigbours as our ſelves at the leaſt, ſo much more our Prince, and Countrey, above our ſelves, as the hand doth the head.</p>
                  <p>And greater and truer love cannot be expreſſed, than by long miſery and durance for the Truth, like an Anchor under Waves, to hold faſt the great Soul of ones Prince (compoſed of Grace and Mercy, and the fear of God,) by his Bowels and Compaſſion, ſtronger than any Cable, from running againſt Eternal Rocks, and claſhing with His Heavenly Sovereign; which is the firſt, and Original diſloyalty, and inſurrection againſt the <hi>Chief,</hi> whereof the Tumults of ſubjects againſt <hi>Secondary</hi> Mortal Soveraigns, are uſually but copies, and fatal conſequences, by mans manifeſt fault, but Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret righteous judgment, as the fear and ſubjection of the Creature is obſerved by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to be abated and impaired towards <hi>Adam,</hi> after his fall.</p>
                  <p>And no Prince can more deſerve ſuch Matyrial fidelity from Servants, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, than your <hi>R. H.</hi> not only upon the ſcore of Loyalty and Conſcience, common to all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63595:12"/>Princes, but of Perſonal, and peculiar, merit and exemplary frequent fatigues, and hazzards, and lovely deportments on the confines of life and death, for the glory of your Countrey, which your, <hi>R. H.</hi> valued above your Life, and preſent, and hereditary greatneſs, as much, as many mean and vulgar ſpirits, do below their petty ſelfends and differences.</p>
                  <p>And that great ſight cannot eaſily depart from my remembrance of your ſerene Magnanimity, and cheerful unconcernedneſs on Quarter Deck, <hi>June</hi> 3d. <hi>1665.</hi> which betoken'd to my hopes a great diſtance of dangers from your <hi>R. H.,</hi> even then, when Roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deaths hail'd thick about your <hi>R.</hi> Perſon, aod beſprinkled your Buff with the blood of your ever memorable Companions, that fell by you. Such contempt of Death, and the Pomp, and Glory of this World, for the defence of your King, and Country, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a lively reſemblance of that true Christian Charity, which doth the like for Chriſt, and ſouls: and fits the underſtanding to receive, and embrace the truth. And I have juſt cauſe often to bleſs God, for a kind of publick reward then, of my many Prayers in private for your <hi>R. H.</hi> (which was my chief, and ſole Armour in your defence) that your <hi>R. H.</hi> ſhould obſerve, and declare it as an Omen of Victory, annext to the publick Service and Exhortation performed by me the even before the fight, by your <hi>R. H.</hi> appointment, that one of the greateſt Ships of the Enemy, ſhould take fire in that moment in the ſight of both Fleets, reported to be one of the number that were particularly bound to deſtroy you.</p>
                  <p>And why ſhould I diſtruſt in God, or the power of truth, or the ſucceſs of ſincere Love, and Loyalty, but that theſe my proſtrate ſentiments, proved, and preferred, through much patience, before all the <hi>offers</hi> of this World, may not contribute with the Prayers of all good Chriſtians, and farr greater Abilities, and Councels, and the conſideration, and candor of your <hi>R. H.</hi> own breaſt, and Princely Loyalty to God and Truth, the greateſt of all, to beget that ſatisfaction, and ſtability in your <hi>R. H.</hi> as may kindle more Bon-fires in our Streets, than did that your renowned Victory?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quinctius</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> General, proclaiming in the Name of the Senate by ſound of Trumpet, unexpected <hi>Liberty</hi> to all the Cities of <hi>Greece,</hi> then newly <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> as the Nation met to begin their Olimpick-games, did ſo diſcompoſe, and lick up all their inclinations after their ſports, with the ſuddainneſs of the good tydings, that when they could believe it to be true, they could think on nothing elſe; And ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, one upon another, with exceſs of joy and thankfulneſs, to kiſs his hands, and to caſt their Crowns and Garlands at his feet, went nigh, to put him in manifeſt danger of his Life, with their Crowd, and immoderate Tranſports, that forgot all manners and diſtance, had not his great ſtrength of body, and the Vigour of his years, being <hi>33,</hi> ſaith <hi>Livy,</hi> and ſome Content, and ſatisfaction to obſerve whence their Rudeneſs ſprang, ſerved to Reſcue him from the danger of too great love.</p>
                  <p>Such a Jubile to our <hi>Britain,</hi> and ſuch a lovely danger to your <hi>R. H.</hi> (as may be gather'd from the General pulſe) the diſmiſſion of ſome ſoruples would ſoon produce, which many ſuſpect, and fear, but I never did, nor can, (before a ſpecial declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) being ſo over-ruled to the contrary by your Princely Wiſdom and juſtice; for what greater violation of the Law of Nations can there be, (to the diſſolution of all Faith and Truth among men, whereon Allegiance to Princes, and the Peace of the World hang) than openly, or ſecretly, to oppoſe, or prejudice a Religion profeſſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be Renounced? or wherein can the Catholick plaiſter of diſpenſation to equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, mend the matter with Generous and ſober underſtandings, whereby the ſoul is licences'd to be damn'd, to ſave the skin?</p>
                  <p>Leaſt therefore by any pretence, or whiſper of <hi>Right,</hi> or colour of conſcience, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all the fear can lye) your <hi>R. H.</hi> ſhould be miſ-led to eſpouſe unnaturally a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, and <hi>wrong Superiour,</hi> to the mauifeſt dethroning of our <hi>right</hi> Mother Church of <hi>Britain,</hi> more Ancient, as well as more ſound and Orthodox, than the other; I have (leaveing all <hi>ſpeculative</hi> controverſies, and hard queſtions, to Schollers and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,) throughly handled one <hi>Practical</hi> point of plain <hi>Right,</hi> and <hi>Title,</hi> or <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> or the Pretences, and Immunities of both Churches; which will give great light, if not a final end to all the reſt, and which all ſorts of men, as well Lay, as Clergy, are bound to know upon their Duty, and Allegiance to God and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and juſtice, and civility to their Neighbours, least they be betrayed by willful ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, to aid an <hi>Uſurper</hi> againſt the <hi>Right Heir;</hi> wherein no more learning, or Logick is required, to maſter and underſtand the point, but ſo much temper and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as ſerves to hear an Evidence, and diſcern between ſoul and Body, or God and Creature, or Chriſtianity and Heatheniſm, or Loyalty and Treaſon, and to lay <hi>hand</hi> upon <hi>heart,</hi> and to follow, either the Laws of God and Man, whereby all men are <hi>Rul'd,</hi> or fate and Providence, whereby they are <hi>Over-rul'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:63595:12"/>
                  <p>But whether in Gods mercy, or Judgment we are to be freed, or continued under our fears and anxieties, to the fixed, and reſolved in Faith, it ſignifies no more, than putting on a Winter, or a Summer habit, either the militant Garb of Patience, to our great reward and comfort, (and your great account, which alone can abate it,) or the triumphant of thanksgiving, to the mutual ſolace and bliſs of both. But as for the weaker flock, whereof Paternal Princely bowels, and paſtoral charge, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the moſt tender; with what ſecurity and content, will they <hi>lye down beſide the ſtill waters in green Paſtures,</hi> When they ſhall have ſuch a <hi>Shepheard,</hi> to be their guard and back, and a terrour (much leſs a harbour) to the <hi>Roman</hi> Wolves, that would devour them? <hi>How will the Mountains skip like Rams, and our little Hills Like Lambs?</hi> Great and unparallel'd was our joy, for your <hi>R.</hi> Brothers <hi>Reſtoration,</hi> and your own together, to your Antient <hi>Rights,</hi> and Dignities over us, that the whole Nation ſeem'd like men that Dream'd; but ſo great is the ſenſe and fear of <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Slavery</hi> upon them and their Children, more inſupportable than any <hi>Temporal</hi> (which it alſo may draw along with it) that the joy of that day is like to be but a Dream indeed, compared to thoſe exultations, and full content, and ſtreins of hearty Triumphs, (if heart-ſtrings can hold) that ſhall break out in every ſtreet and corner of the whole Nation, with Bon-fires, and Feaſts, and praiſes, reaching up to Heaven, and thence to earth again, in the reſponſes of Angels to our Anthems, at the day of your return, from the danger of errour, to our <hi>Church,</hi> and our <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> and the Truth. That your <hi>R. H.</hi> will be more glorious in the end, than in the beginning, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Victories over temptations, and <hi>Deceitful Guides,</hi> like the Sun after an Eclipſe; which is the preſent truſt, or ſhall ever be, as is ought, the daily Prayer, and Study, and Patience of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Royal Highneſs, moſt Humble, moſt Dutyful and Faithful Servant</hi> Thomas Jones.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>For the Right Reverend Dr. <hi>Barrow</hi> Lord Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph.</hi> At <hi>Ely Houſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My LORD,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I am inform'd that your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> concerns your ſelf with other Reverend Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in other parts, to bring new trouble and diſgrace upon me, ſince my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration to <hi>Landurnog</hi> (which is within your Dioceſs and Neighborhood, but out of your Juriſdiction) and to begin to give directions to your Clergie, to avoid and ſhun my company and converſe, as a perfidious Perſon.</p>
                  <p>I truſt, I am no way guilty of that hard Character, or any other Crime, have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lived all my days, juſt to all men, and firm to my King and Church, though wholly a ſtranger to your <hi>Lordſhip.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I was born, and brought up at <hi>Oſweſtry</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> and lived in the late times at <hi>Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Montgomeriſhire,</hi> both within your Dioceſs; where it is well known, and well atteſted by the Principal Gentry and Clergy of thoſe parts, how far ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable I was to King and Church, againſt their Enemies, <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagators,</hi> with conſiderable ſucceſs, though with Perſecution: Whither I repair'd at the requeſt and advice of the Loyal Gentry and Clergy thereabouts, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly Dr. <hi>Griffiths</hi> (afterwards one of your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> predeceſſors) and left a fellowſhip in Univerſity <hi>Colledg,</hi> and took Holy-Orders in 1654. and ſtudied the welſh Tongue, to ſerve thoſe parts, when the <hi>Orthodoxe</hi> Clergy was miſerably conſum'd, by an act of Propagation ſo called. The Title ſtood thus (as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me upon beſt enquiry) <hi>Puleſton</hi> the laſt Lawful incumbent dyed <hi>Anno.</hi> 1645. <hi>Wyn</hi> the next was put in by Parliament Committees, &amp; put out again by the ſame powers, for ſcandal about 1651 And the Church ſhut up till 1654. when I and others were deſired to come from <hi>Oxford</hi> to the aſſiſtance of the Country to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Taylors and Weavers <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſetling upon the Pariſhes. Upon his Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration, <hi>Wyn</hi> diſcovers a dormant Title (ſimoniacally procur'd about 1646) the Commiſſioners for conſirming and reſtoring, with the advice of Biſhop <hi>Griffiths,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their hearing of the cauſe between <hi>Wyn</hi> and me, ſetled me, becauſe <hi>Wyn</hi> had not read the 39 Articles: <hi>Wyn</hi> afterwards at a tryal at Law at <hi>Bridgenorth,</hi> had one to prove his reading the Articles, and I was Ejected. Then Biſhop <hi>Griffiths</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives <hi>Wyn</hi> in his conſiſtory for ſcandal, and confers <hi>Caſtle</hi> on <hi>Langford</hi> a monyed man, &amp;c. <hi>Wyn</hi> appeals and overthrows the Biſhop, who lived not long after.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63595:13"/>
                  <p>This Rectory being worth 140 pound, <hi>per Annum</hi> I abode the loſs thereof, with much arrears, rather than I would recover the ſame, by bringing the frailties of ſuch Patrons upon the Stage, whereof I had good proofs offerd me, and have them by me.</p>
                  <p>From thence I removed to the ſervice of the Lord Preſident and Councel of <hi>Wales</hi> at <hi>Ludlow Caſtle,</hi> Recommended by the <hi>R</hi> Biſhops of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> and St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> about 1661. and thence to His R. Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York</hi> in 1663. upon no intereſt or acquaintance, but after ſome Sermons Preached by me in <hi>Weſtminiſter-Abby,</hi> and about the ſame time waved an Invitation from Dr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getſon</hi> the moſt R. Primate of <hi>England,</hi> to be His Graces Chaplain, thinking it not fit to deſert the Duke on a ſuddain for advantage, in all which places, (which are the ſtages of my life,) I lived in good Name, and Fame, and Love, untill I fell into the diſpleaſure of the Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Winton,</hi> (and my Lords Grace of <hi>Canterbury</hi> upon his ſcore) to whom I was as much a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as to your Lordſhip, (ſaving that I was recommended by an Eminent hand unto the one for Loyal actings and ſufferings in the late times) who became in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorable towards me, from 1666 and before, to this preſent time, for no real cauſe, as I could ever find or conjecture, but recommending one De <hi>Macedo,</hi> (being In great diſtreſs and want upon his leaving the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>) to Her late R. Highneſs's Charity, (then very zealous for Proteſtantiſme) who proving a great Eye-ſore to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Chappel at St <hi>James</hi>'s, upon Her Highneſs's countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of him, was ſtrangely removed out of the way after <hi>I</hi> went to Sea to attend the Duke in 1664 and 1665. But if he (through provocation or diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement or ſcandal given him) carried himſelf unworthy of his maintenance and reſpect, which he received from the Dutches, and alſo from my Lord of <hi>W.,</hi> he might ſurely have been laid aſide with Engliſh Chriſtian fairneſs, (being a ſtranger) without arts and Snare, and the fowl imputations of being burnt for Sodomy in <hi>Paris,</hi> about ten years before he died, and without annexing my diſtruction to his eſcape at <hi>Portſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> (whore he had like to have been conveyed to be more really burnt in his own Country) By whoſe means this was contriv'd, deſerves enquiry, but my fall was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly then wrought, by the means of the ſaid Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> through her ſaid Highneſs, (whoſe reputed Confeſſor he then was) againſt the Dukes mind and inclination, when I was newly returned from Sea, with the ſpecial and publick approbation of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.<note place="margin">Vide S. Creſſy Epiſtle Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logetical, Pag. 115. Apology for the <hi>Papiſts</hi> anſwered pag. 36.</note> A preſage and proem to this trouble, was the late Lord high Chancellor <hi>H.</hi> deſiring me not to take my degree of Dr. when I moved him for his letter, As Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of the Univerſity (granted of Courſe to any) being recommended to his favour by the Duke a little before. Shortly after the great Biſhops accuſe an innocent Servant to his Prince and Maſter, who had but newly before recommended me to them; The exceptions were (1.) That the Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> having adviz'd the Duke to have no Preaching at Sea, I ſhould ſpeak irreverently hereof to a friend (as contrary to a Fleet Statute and Sea mens needs, as well as out of preſent pique againſt me.) 2. That I ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n'd to Adminiſter the Sacrament to the Family in the abſence of the Dutches. 3. That I was an enemy to the Governours, and Government of the Church. But they were ſoon waved and quitted, as ſoon a <hi>I</hi> pleaded innocence, and deſired to be tryed upon any of them, or any other, and the Duke acquainted, that now my Croſs was without a Title. But though <hi>I</hi> was cleard, <hi>I</hi> was nevertheleſs remov'd (whether <hi>I</hi> would or no) to <hi>Landurnog</hi> (uſually held in commendam and reſided upon by the Biſhops of <hi>Bangor</hi>) under coulour of preferment, and reward for ſervice. Her Highneſs being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, as ſhe was pleaſ'd to declare to me before the Duke, that I could not hold the Dukes ſervice and my living together with a good Conſcience: whereupon His Highneſs commanded me, to go to a great Biſhop to deſire him, as from his Highneſs to ſee me ſetled by Law in both: and the great Biſhops anſwer to His Highneſs meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage was, that he had not learning enough to ſatisfy His Highneſs, how by Law one body could be in two places, but the Duke overrul'd for me, and ſecur'd me his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whereupon my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> ſent for me to tell me, that the Dutches did deſire him to reſt, becauſe the Duke was ſo firm unto me, and he promiſed to reſt, and to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me no more in the Houſe, and deſired me to confide therein, for he would take his remedy at Law for the words pretended to be ſpoken by me touching his prohibiting preaching at Sea, and my credulity was my ruine, for in few dayes the Duke was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by them, and I diſmiſſed his Service, and delivered over to the mercy of my Enemies: one of His Highneſs bedchamber undeſir'd, then Interpoſed, will your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deſert your Chaplain, who ſtuck to you in your dangers, and you have publickly commended, it will not be for your Highneſs's Honour, and the Dukes anſwer was, <hi>The Biſhops are againſt him:</hi> So I was diſmiſſed not for any crime, but ſome ſecret expedient.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63595:13"/>
                  <p>About a Month before I was diſmiſſed, the Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> had excited Dr. <hi>Morgan</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi> againſt me, at his Conſecration at <hi>Lambeth, July</hi> 1. 1666. in theſe or the like words, to my face, (Mr. <hi>S. Ll.</hi> my Dioceſans Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain being then preſent) either he, or I am the erranſt Rogue in <hi>England,</hi> uſe him accordingly when he comes to his Living: to which I then made no reply. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, ſhortly after I was diſmiſs'd, the late Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> (whom a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Honour deſired to intercede for me) told me (that for the words touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Preaching at Sea) my Lord of <hi>Winton</hi> would perſecute me to the utmoſt of his Power, whereſoever I went, whom I then anſwered, that I would put on a Patience as large as his Power. Accordingly the ſaid Biſhop of <hi>Bangor,</hi> (when I refuſed to exchange <hi>Landurnog</hi> worth 160. <hi>l.</hi> with him for <hi>Lanvair,</hi> worth but 50. <hi>l per ann.</hi>) began to trouble me in my living; He, his Chaplains, Mr. <hi>S. Ll.</hi> and Mr. <hi>G.</hi> having by threats, and promiſes to ſave harmleſs, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments, procured illiterate Church-Wardens (new-comers to <hi>Landurnog</hi>) to make a preſentment againſt me about <hi>Auguſt</hi> (1668.) (an unuſual time) for not reading Prayers in the uſual and moſt convenient place, contrary to the truth, and the Judgment of all the Pariſh, and their own Inclination; to ground his proceedings upon, <hi>(ſee depoſitions in the Arches)</hi> they commenced a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie in his conſiſtory againſt me for not reading Prayers, in the antient, uſual, and moſt convenient place (for want of other exceptions,) the frivolouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs whereof, in the ſenſe of all the Country, if your Lordſhip hath not heard, your Intelligence in that Neighbourhood is very ſhort.) And denying upon his Oath in the Arches his Order that he had given, upon <hi>M. H.</hi> moneys towards a new reading Pew, which lay croſs to his proceedings, cauſed me to be cenſured <hi>ab Officio &amp; beneficio,</hi> upon a pretended diſobedience to an Order that was contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: And no ſubmiſſion for any poſſible miſapprehenſion would be accepted by the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, or his great Agents therein, to Salve my Canonical Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or my Function, or my Chriſtian Communion; but I muſt confeſs ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute diſobedience, being certain or the contrary. And their unjuſt Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of me, upon this ſole pretence, pronounced againſt me, <hi>nomine Chriſti implorato,</hi> laſted againſt me for a long ſpace of time, as if they meant to make me an Inſidel, or a Schiſmatique: yet one of the Judges delegates the late Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> did not like the proceedings, and appeared afterwards for me: But this Curſe and Cenſure was worn and blown off at laſt by providence, and my Patient enduring the Law. And how farr the guilt thereof reverts and ſtayes upon the Authors, and ſtrong Abbettors, in the ſight of God and reaſon, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to primitive Rules, your Lordſhips Learning can better tell. <hi>Photij Nomocanon tit.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>Waiting on my Dioceſan, <hi>Octob.</hi> 3. 1668. at <hi>Lanynnis</hi> to render an account of my Obedience to his Order, and to prevent (what lay in me) ſuch a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous frivolous controverſie in the eſteem of all people; he then and there minds and ubraids me to my face, (as he did often behind my back, as I heard, to weaken me) with my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> Character at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> now ſeconded with my rejection from the Duke, of the one, or the other, being a great Rogue, and that he was not to believe the Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> to be ſuch. To which Ianſwered, that my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> had no reaſon for his diſpleaſure, or ſuch his Character of me, but my introducing the <hi>Portugues</hi> aforeſaid, and the Dukes favour, and deſired my Dioceſan's aſſiſtance to have this matter ſearched, by competent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and I examined, of what I had ſeen and obſerved, when I lived at Saint <hi>James,</hi> (leaſt there were any deſign laid againſt this Church) and I ſhould then befound an honeſt man, being very careful, for ſeveral reaſons, from affirming any thing poſitively, of ſo great a Perſon, as my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> But to leave that part to thoſe, to whom it belonged to Judge, and deſired my Dioceſan, then and there, to take particular notice of the tenour of my diſcourſe againſt private affirming, and judging of ſuperiours. Do you intend then, ſaid my Dioceſan to me to make me an Informer, to which I anſwered, that as he had more maintenance and honour from the Church, ſo he ought the more to appear in its Defence, and my Teſtimony would better come in, when introduced by his Lordſhip.</p>
                  <p>But there was nothing done in ſeveral Months upon this panage between us, onely all manner of unfavourable proceedings uſed againſt me in the matter of the Reading Pew, when my Dioceſan came again to <hi>Llanynnis,</hi> in <hi>May,</hi> 1669. I then delivered him in Writing under my hand, the ſum of the aforeſaid Diſcourſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63595:14"/>uſed <hi>Octob.</hi> 3. 1668. at the ſame place touching my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> for his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter certainty, Biſhop <hi>G.</hi> of Saint <hi>Aſaph</hi> being then preſent. The paſſage in the ſaid paper, being thus; That the ſame time (<hi>viz. Oct.</hi> 3. 1668. <hi>Jones</hi> did, and doth ſubmit his whole Life for 30 Years backward, to the ſtricteſt examination of my Lord of <hi>Winton</hi> and <hi>Bangor</hi> (who have ſufficient Power and Juriſdiction over him, And if in all that time no flaw, or blame can be found in his Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Converſation, or Principles, he then did, and ſtill doth declare, that the true cauſe of my Lord of <hi>Winton</hi>'s Wrath and War againſt him was, Firſt, his Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of a <hi>Portugues</hi> Noble-man Convert, to her R. Highneſs Favour and Charity, who complains, (and <hi>Jones</hi> conceaves not without grounds) of wrongs and Snares againſt his life, from my Lord of <hi>Winton,</hi> who for his quality and unblameable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (confeſſed by his adverſaries) was uſeful, while encouraged, to prevent the growth of Popery (which <hi>Jones</hi> had ſpeciall orders to endeavour) in (and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout) his R. Highneſs Family, whereof he had charge of Souls, and by that, and other Inſtances did effect, with Gods aſſiſtance, in good part; Secondly when his R. Highneſs began kindly and frequently to mention <hi>Jones</hi> his performance of his Duty with him at Sea, and eſpecially when his Majeſty and Highneſs were pleaſed to point at him in the Royal Chappel in time of Divine Service in view of many, my Lord of <hi>Winton</hi> from that time, never ceas'd to imploy his utmoſt Power and Intereſt to ruine <hi>Jones</hi> in Court and Country.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jones</hi> therefore doth humbly deſire, the right Reverend Biſhops of <hi>Bangor</hi> and St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> to cauſe this Matter to be ſearch'd, leaſt there be any deſign, laid againſt this Church; or Judgments he multiplied upon this Nation by unſincere Oaths, or the Presbyter party bearian away the Glory of Defending the Proteſtant Intereſt, and the late glorious Kings Cauſe and Martyrdome recieve wrong, and old Fears and jealouſies be juſtified. And Particularly leaſt by any miſinformation, <hi>Jones</hi> be oppreſſed by the Church, for his fidelity to the Church, as well againſt the Schiſmatical party, when it formerly prevail'd, as againſt the Popiſh, when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Clandeſtinely to prevaile.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>May</hi> 26. 1669. <hi>Tho. Jones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither was there any thing made of, or upon this Information in writeing (ſaving the ſending a Copy atteſted by a Public notary, to the great Biſhops) for the compaſs of a whole Year (my Lord <hi>Ch. H.</hi> being now out of the way, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) But in the Year 1670, when I was purſuing my appeal to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches againſt my Dioceſan, touching the ſaid reading <hi>Pew,</hi> my Dioceſan and my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> Conſulted upon an Action of <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> which my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> Commenc'd againſt me in <hi>Eaſter</hi> Term of the ſaid Year 1670, for words pretended to have been ſpoken by me at <hi>Lanynnis, Octob.</hi> 3. 1668. and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their Importance were, ſo long conceal'd. The words of my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration (put in <hi>Trinity</hi> Term following,) where theſe. My Lord of <hi>W.</hi> hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged you (Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi>) to do me all the miſchief you can, for his part, he hath diſcountenanc'd my Catechizing at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, and my Preaching in the <hi>Fleet;</hi> he is a Promotor of Popery, and a Subvertor of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which words, I mean the laſt Clauſe, as ſoon as I met them in the Declaration, I was amaz'd thereat, and declared to my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> Agents and Friends, (for I could not be admitted either before or after to ſpeake with his Lordſhip,) that I never ſpoke thoſe words, neither did I own them; I and an other then and there preſent would take our Oaths upon it; what I did ſpeake of my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> I gave the ſame under my hand in writing, which I did own and ſtand to: my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> notwithſtanding would proceed upon theſe words: But in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term he was not ready, and I had an opportunity to be diſmiſſ'd upon motion, being the third Term, as I was informed, and my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> could never have renewed this ſuite any more, becauſe of the Statute of limitation: Here my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> is beholding for his verdict and conqueſt to my reſpects to the late Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> (where of both were told betimes) who pretending kindneſs to me, and good Will, did advize and prevaile upon me to deſiſt. <hi>Hillary</hi> Term 1670, the Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi> and his Chaplain and Mr. <hi>S. Ll.</hi> Swore the words aforeſaid at Kings Bench before Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Keeling, Middleſex,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ll. ex abundante</hi> Swore, that I there ſaid, I delighted to contend with great Biſhops, which was a great Colluſion, for I had us'd thoſe words there, by way of diſowning, and charge againſt the ſaid Mr, <hi>Ll.</hi> for raiſing in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63595:14"/>Country ſuch a falſe report concerning me, who delighted not to contend with any ſort of men, either ſuperiors, or Inferiours, or equalls, for reaſons which I then and there gave to them both.</p>
                  <p>My Lord of <hi>W.</hi> having recover'd a verdict of 317 <hi>l.</hi> againſt me for the words ſo proved, ſeiz'd upon my Living of <hi>Llandurnog,</hi> which was all my preferment, for three Years together for the ſame (being worth 200 <hi>l. per annum</hi> at leaſt in thoſe years, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there hapned a dearth in thoſe parts) not allowing me 6 <hi>d.</hi> thereout towards my main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, being ſilenc'd alſo from my calling the ſaid years in the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, upon the ſcore of reading <hi>Pew</hi> aforeſaid. My Lord of <hi>W.</hi> and his Friends, about the ſaid three years end, by trick about 20 <hi>l.</hi> (being my own moneys in <hi>over-plus,</hi> for which they gain'd a receipt from under my hand by craft,) have raiſed a report thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he ſecretly maintained me in thoſe years, wronging my next Relations, who ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did, to whom I am to Leaſe <hi>Llandurnog</hi> from time, to time for their reimburſements; yet my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> Lawyers affirm'd at the King's Bench, that he had beſtowed the verdict moneys, ſaving 50 <hi>l.</hi> upon <hi>Bangor</hi> Cathedral, the ſaid, Court wondring at ſo cruel a Charity, neither of which vain glorious reports were true, moſt of the moneys being ſtill in the hands of his Sequeſtrators, towards uſes limited by a Deed kept ſecret, as I have been credibly inform'd. Though his Lordſhip had received (or might have received) all his moneys well nigh twice over, yet he ſtill withheld my Living from me till I mov'd the Court of Kings Bench, <hi>Trin.</hi> 1674, where the late Biſhop of <hi>Bangor,</hi> his principal Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, being detected in Illegal malitious proceedings, eſcap'd being fined by the Court for the ſame, by a Plea of Death in his behalf.</p>
                  <p>Neither was I wanting to tender my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> through Perſons of Quality and honour ſuch a Submiſſion betimes (as was due <hi>foro ſoli,</hi> upon ſuch words prov'd againſt me) which I can well ſwear I never ſpoke: and upon his refuſal of the ſame, yielded to pay him his Monyes quietly rather, then make any accknowledgment againſt my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which he expected. The Duke of <hi>York</hi> the ſame time <hi>vz</hi> 1671, was graciouſly pleas'd to intercede through the late Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> for remiſſion of his verdict, and an end of troubling me. And my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> promiſed by his ſecretary Mr. <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard,</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> that he did remit the ſame upon the Duke's Account, as the Biſhop told me, but then went ſoon off from that promiſe, ſequeſtring me a new (as it were) in my belief and hopes.</p>
                  <p>Now it is to be obſerv'd, my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> never made any manner of vindication againſt the ſaid paper, which I did always own; and have been ſince more Confirm'd in, by the Rumour'd Inſtability of her late Highneſs in 1671, (whereof I had Apprehenfions to my ſelf in 1666,) and as I adhaer'd to my opinion deliver'd in the ſaid paper from the date thereof to this preſent, amidſt variety of Deaths, ſo, God helping, I ſhall continue in the ſame, Martyrially, to my lifes end, unleſs I be convinc'd there from by better Methods, then have hitherto been uſed, <hi>Vid.</hi> Mercyleſs preſſures without any end, upon wilful miſconſtruction of my words; offers of great preferments, Dukes favour, and ſums of monies in my ſtreights, if I make ſome confeſſion againſt the Truth, and my ſelf, to clear my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> which hath been term'd Submiſſion, and due Obedience to Superiours: deterring of my Friends and acquantance from me, inceſing great Perſons every where againſt me, and perhaps your Lordſhip, allowing me no more right to their Truth, than if I were an Heretick, or ſome Vermine. And which argues much guilt and fear, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing my repute, by ſpreading a report in Court and Country, that I am diſtracted and mad, contrary to their own belief and knowledg, becauſe contradictory to all their other proceedings. And this my opinion, is in a manner confeſſed, and given for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by the parties themſelves, by ſeveral late experiences, 1. In an eminent and great Divine, who concern'd himſelf alike, to charge me lately about this matter, but was forc'd to retreat upon this Plea: 2. In a great friend of my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> (privy and Inſtrumental to all his original diſpleaſure againſt me, but ſince a Penitent,) who upon my Caſe ſo ſtated and read to him, could not aſſign any other real cauſe beſides, and in my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> himſelf, to whoſe Conſcience I put it, in my Letter of the 13th Inſtant. And neither he nor they, nor your Lordſhip to their aſſiſtance, have or can aſſigne any real cauſe in all my life, adaequate and proportionable to ſuch laſting wrath, beſides that alone of the ſaid <hi>Portugues</hi> his Introduction, and my actings ſo timely againſt the unſufferable encroachments of Popery about St. <hi>James</hi> (then too much conniv'd at) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my place, and truſt, and orders; and fidelity to my Royal Maſters Intereſt, and Love in theſe Proteſtant Nations, and thoſe Oaths alſo of Allegiance and Supremacy, which your Lordſhip, and your R. Brethren have taken, and Adminiſter daily to your Inferiour Clergy. And if ſo, then my wrongs and ſufferings, become your own, and the wrongs of any other true and ſound Father, or Son
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63595:15"/>of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the wrongs of any other ſincere Proteſtant whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and in all equity your Lordſhip ought to aſſiſt and aid me, and procure as many as you can of your R. Brethren to do the like, (becauſe I am ſo over powr'd) and to bring the matter to examination according to the Import of that Britiſh proverb.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Nid gwaeth Cywir er i chwilio</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>I may venture to ſay, no <hi>Romiſh</hi> Preiſt or Domeſtique Nonconformiſt (I ſpeak not from envy to them) hath been known to be ſo continually followed and annoyed, by Sea and Land, by Court and Country, for Ten or Eleaven Years together, as I have been, and that by one Proteſtant Father of this Church, (for I ſuppoſe the reſt that appear'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me were miſlead derivately from him although it be well known to the World, that I am, and ever was a declar'd Porteſtant, always conformable to the Laws of this Church and Nation, and open to no other exceptions againſt my life and Principles, But, thoſe two Contriv'd asperſions of Reading pew, and <hi>Sandalum</hi> pretended, which by Gods good providence begin to turn to my Credit, and my Enamies thame and contradictions. I hoped rather to have been approv'd and encourag'd by one in my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> place and truſt, for my ſincere Actings, than ſuddainly deſtroyed amidſt freſh favour, for no other cauſe, but my adhaering to the Church, and the Truth in wavering times (which your Lordſhip is pleas'd to call perfidiouſneſs in me: others, Pride, Cbſtinacy, (as if car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal fear and Compliance, were true Humility) I have obſerv'd after ſome Mortality, and changes of Affairs, and Credibly heard that my Lord of <hi>W.</hi> of late hath ſhewed his Zeal for Proteſtantiſme, even to extreams, as they ſay, but he ſtill continues more hard to be entreated towards me than ever, perhaps for putting him on ſuch neceſſity.</p>
                  <p>Particularly in point of Juſtice, my Lord, as you are a Chriſtian Biſhop, fearing God (for the ninth Commandment reaches your Spiritual Lordſhips as well as other Mortals,) I humbly expect and require, that either your Lordſhip make good your charge afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or any other, if you can; or that you recal effectually your deſamation, and Inhibitions againſt my converſe, which from a Perſon of your Authority are very praejudical to my good name and calling amongſt my Friends and Relations and Charge, and therefore very hard to be endur'd.</p>
                  <p>Its conceav'd my Friends and Defenders are fewer, and my Enemies more in number and combination (than perhaps they would be) by reaſon of my over-much patience and forbearing to make my Caſe fully known to good men, and to the World, againſt the ways of my Potent Accuſers; which is the reaſon I have put ſo large a trouble upon your Lordſhip, and ſhall be further ready to give ampler ſatisfaction, in Caſe of any doubt or ſcruple, whereby others, as well as your Lordſhip, may the better eſcape that ſpiritual Infelicity mentioned by our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.7. of condemning the Innocent, where it becomes a duty rather to open mouths in their defence.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, No man ſhall be more ready to expreſs all Honour, Reverence, Obedience, and Submiſſion to your Losdſhip, and all Perſons of your Degree and Dignity, (as far as Allegiance and Fidelity to King, Laws, Oaths, and Truth will permit, than</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Decemb.</hi> 28. 1675.</date> 
                        <hi>At Mr.</hi> S. <hi>Apothecary at the Black Spread-Eagle near</hi> Arundel <hi>Houſe.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your Humble Servant, <hi>Tho. Jones.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <head>A POSTSCRIP.</head>
                     <p>Some Facts that herein occur touching Deceaſed, or great Perſons, which none elſe could know, I relate as in the preſence of God, to diſcover the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked truth, for my own neceſſary defence: and for publick uſe, if there be need. <hi>T. J.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> within concerned, ſent his Secretary to my Lodging, <hi>Jan.</hi> 4. following to acquaint: That his Lordſhip had not ſpoak any ſuch words againſt me: That he reproved his Brother the Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi> for troubling me about ſuch a frivolous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as was the Reading-Pew; That he was a ſtranger to me, that I might have the paper back again, if I deſired it.</p>
            <p>I anſwered, that I had a Copy of it: That it was fit it ſhould be communicated to his Reverend Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to know what they had to except; That if I ſuffer'd for my Fidelity to the Church (in a time of Tryal) it was fit the Biſhops ſhould defend me, before any others; he replied, That his Lordſhip had ſhewed the ſame already to the <hi>B. R.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I have heard of no exceptions againſt it from that time to this. The ſaid Biſhop never appearing after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards at <hi>London</hi> in ſeveral Years, and at his Death, ordering a ſtrange Inſcription for his Grave in St. <hi>Aſaph Cathedral,</hi> which is called by the Neighbours in Britiſh, <hi>Eſcob-Ty. i. e.</hi> The Biſhops Houſe.</p>
            <p>About <hi>April,</hi> 1676. This paper was ſhewed to Sir <hi>T. M.</hi> and <hi>S. T. C.</hi> of the Houſe of Commons, and the ſubſtance thereof in <hi>Decemb.</hi> 78. to an Honourable and Right Beverend Privy-Councceiler: and the B. of <hi>W.</hi> ſent for thereupon to <hi>London</hi> to Recover the Duke to our Church (who had ſo ſtrenuouſly kept his Dutcheſs from Revolting from us). So much the pretence and covering of a Bigid Calviniſt, had impoſed upon the Beſt, and Wiſeſt, and Greateſt.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63595:15"/>
                        <head>A Depoſition in the Arches, taken <hi>January 1669. Inter Jones</hi> Appellant, <hi>&amp; Ridge &amp; Jones, &amp; Epiſcopum</hi> Bangor <hi>Appellat,</hi> touching the riſe and Occaſion of the Action of <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> in the Courts Temporal, and controverſies about Reading Pew in Courts Eccleſiaſtical.</head>
                        <p>THe ſaid Appellant the Third day of <hi>October</hi> laſt was Twelve-month, went to the ſaid <hi>Simon Lloid's</hi> Houſe, to wait on the Biſhop, and render him an account of the Letter he had formerly received from him, whereby the appellant was requir'd to read in the moſt uſual Reading ſeat, in the Church, and being asked by the Biſhop, why he did not obey the ſaid Letter of his, the Appellant anſwered he did obey him, by Reading where his Predeceſſors, Rectors of the ſaid Pariſh had formerly Read, whereupon the Biſhop ſaid, he intended the Curat's ſeat, the Appellant replied, his Lordſhip had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the ſame as unfit and undecent, giving him to underſtand, where, and when, and upon what account, which the ſaid Appellant Related to the Effect following, that is to ſay, for that he had acquainted his Lordſhip, that ſome of the moſt Eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Pariſh had complained unto him, they could neither ſee, nor hear him read in the ſaid Curates Seat, and withal that he had Forty Shillings given him by a Perſon of Quality in or about St. <hi>Jams</hi>'s Court, to be diſpoſed off in the ſaid Church, to ſupply what was wanting therein, and that after the Biſhop had Enquired what was wanting therein, and being told by the appellant the Curat's ſeat was undecent, and diſlik'd, and complain'd of, as aforeſaid, his Lordſhip Ordered the Appellant to publiſh the unfitneſs thereof, and that the Pariſh ſhould erect a new Decent Seat, more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Body of the Church, and that ſuch as ſhould be aggrieved thereat, ſhould repair to his Lordſhip to <hi>Ruthin,</hi> where a Correction or Viſitation was to be kept, to give him the reaſon of their grievance, and alſo that the Pariſh ſhould contribute Twenty Shillings more to the ſaid Forty Shillings for the Purpoſe aforeſaid, which publication the ſaid <hi>Simon Lloyd</hi> ſaid was not true, ſaying, we ſhould have heard of it, if it had been ſo, or words to that Effect, whereupon the Biſhop asked the Appellant, whether he had ſuch Order under his Hand? And the Appellant, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he had not under his hand, but by word of Mouth, the Biſhop replyed and ſaid, I deny I gave you ſuch Order, my Word ſhall be taken before your Oath, meaning the ſaid Appellants, and told the ſaid Appellant Three times over, he Lyed, and ſaid unto him, you muſt contend with great Biſhops, I will Order you, whereupon the Appellant ſaid, that the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> had provok'd his Lordſhip againſt him, for he the ſaid Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> ſaid to his Lordſhip, in preſence of the Appellant, that he the Appellant was the Erranſt Rogue in <hi>England,</hi> or elſe he the ſaid Biſhop was, uſe him accordingly when he comes to his Living, which ſayings, or words to that Effect, the Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi> did then admit where ſpoken by the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> wherupon the Appellant deſired to be Examined before ſome competent Judicatory touching a great concern of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to which the Biſhop anſwered, and ſaid, what, will you make me an Informer? or the like Effect paſt then between them.</p>
                        <p>And further ſaith, and believes it to be true, that the ſaid Biſhop long before this cauſleſs Trouble and Moleſtation ſent his Chaplains, <hi>Gethin</hi> and <hi>Lloyd,</hi> unto him, deſiring him to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change his Rectory for another Benefice the ſaid Biſhop would give for it, which offer the Appellant refuſing, was the occaſion of his Perſecution, as this deponent verily believes, and the ſaid Biſhop having often times decalred a liking to the ſaid Rectory, as this Deponent was credibly informed by ſeveral of the beſt of the Pariſh, by all which proceedings, and practices, it is manifeſt what wrong the Appellant hath had, Occaſioned as this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent believes, for refuſing to Exchange his Rectory aforeſaid, and laſtly this Deponent ſaith and believeth, that the ſaid Appellant did not at at all diſobey the Biſhops Commands, but in reſpect of the Contradictions thereof, he knew not how to obey him, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing or rendring himſelf Guilty, of Publiſhing an untruth at the Altar, which if the Appellant had yeilded unto, this Deponent believes the Biſhop would ſoon have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Advantage thereof to expell him his Rectory, ſo much deſir'd by the Biſhop, and if this Deponent had not been Privy to moſt of the aforeſaid proceeding, he would hardly have believed a Reverend Perſon would have acted ſuch things.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>William Jones</hi> Gentleman.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>When I could not prevent the trouble, to prevent the ſcandal of this Controrverſy on my ſide, I declared in my Church on a Sunday about the the latter end of <hi>October</hi> 1668. That it was the Duty of a Clerk by his Oath to be Obedient to his Dioceſan; That I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63595:16"/>left Reading in the Curate Seat in Obedienceto my Dioceſan, who judg'd it Unfit to Read Prayers in; That I continued to Read Prayers in this Upper Seat, in obedience to my Dioceſans preſent monition, to Read <hi>Loco conſueto &amp; maxime Convenienti,</hi> in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom'd and moſt convenient place, as all of you agree this Seat to be, that I was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and willing to Officiate in any other Third place the Biſhop and the Pariſh ſhall agree, which declaration is atteſted by Numbers of my Pariſhoners upon their Oaths in the Arches, <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet by the Influence of the Two great Biſhops and their Creatures, Sir <hi>Leolin Jenkyns, B. R.</hi> and others, I was condemned and cenſured <hi>ab Officio &amp; beneficio</hi> at the Arches and Delegates, as well as at the Court of <hi>Bangor,</hi> and no acknowledgement of a Poſſible miſtake would be admitted to reſtore me unto my calling unleſs I did confeſs and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg an abſolute diſobedience to my Dioceſan, which I knew whither it tended, and I reſolved to appeal to Heaven, by patient ſuffering, againſt ſuch Diabolical contrivance, (as it ſeem'd to me) till God relieved me by the Death of my Dioceſan, and an Act of Grace in 1672. whereby both Cenſures, and the conditional coſts, were extinguiſhed as the Biſhop of <hi>R.</hi> acknowledged being the only Judge Delegate (ſaving one other) ſurviving and favouring at firſt my Dioceſans-ſide, but yet my preſent Dioceſan inſiſted, I ſhould take Abſolution, before I Officiated in his Dioceſs, which I ever refuſed to do, before either the Act of Oblivion, or the Death of my former Biſhop, becauſe Innocent.</p>
            <p>My Dioceſan chuſing rather to proceed againſt me in the matter of the Reading Pew, than to aſſiſt me, to be Examin'd touching the Churches Danger, which I ſuſpected, Hearing of the Meeting of another Biſhop in the Neighbourhood, I delivered to both, the following Paper, <hi>May,</hi> 26. 1669.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> his Caſe, Rector of <hi>Landurnog</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> Chaplain attending his Royal Highneſs, at St. <hi>James,</hi> and abroad, humbly preſented to the Right Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in God, the Biſhops of <hi>Bangor</hi> and St. <hi>Aſaph;</hi> at <hi>Lannunnis</hi> in <hi>Dyſſrin Cluid, May 26. 1669.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THat on the firſt of <hi>July</hi> 1666. at a Conſecration Dinner at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> it pleaſed the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>George</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Winton</hi> to incenſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Biſhop of <hi>Bangor,</hi> Mr <hi>Jones</hi> his Dioceſan, in theſe or the like words, That he was the Errant'ſt Rogue in <hi>England,</hi> and that my Lord of <hi>Bangor</hi> ſhould uſe him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly when he came to his Living.</p>
                  <p>That from that time, and eſpecially from <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1668. (after other Attempts fail'd) upon a pretence about a Reading ſeat in the Pariſh Church of <hi>Landurnog,</hi> my Lord of <hi>Bangor</hi> did ſufficiently anſwer and gratifie my Lord of <hi>Wintons</hi> pleaſure touching Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> by all manner of unfavourable proceedings, Excommunications, Cenſures <hi>ab ingreſſu Eccleſiae, ab Officio &amp; Beneficio,</hi> and other defamations againſt Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> the Living being in my Lord of <hi>Bangors</hi> own Gift and Patronage.</p>
                  <p>That Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> upon Appeal being reſtored to his Church, <hi>March</hi> 14. 1668. Did by way of Appology Verify his Life and Innocence from his Infancy at the Altar (for the ſatisfaction of his Pariſhoners) in point of Loyalty, and Principles, and converſation; and particularly his Obedience to his Dioceſan, touching the Reading Seat, declaring there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal, that my Lord of <hi>Winton</hi> who had privately accuſed Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> to his R. Maſter, and diligently incens'd ſeveral great Perſons in Church and State againſt him, was driv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to wave and clear Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> from all manner of Charge, and exception againſt him, before he was willing to accept, or repair to his Living at <hi>Landurnog</hi> (the uſual Reſidence by Commendam of the Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi>) he having before refuſed the Biſhoprick it ſelf preferring his R. Highneſs Rays and Service before an untimely Dignity.</p>
                  <p>That the ſame time Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> did, and doth ſubmit his whole life for Thirty Years Backward to the ſtricteſt Examination of my Lord of <hi>Winton</hi> and <hi>Bangor,</hi> (who have ſufficient jurisdiction and Power over him) and <hi>If in all that time,</hi> no Flaw or blame can be found in his Loyalty, converſation, or Principles, <hi>He then did, and ſtill doth Declare,</hi> that the true cauſe of my Lord of <hi>Wintons</hi> Wrath and War againſt him, was, Firſt his intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of a Portugues Nobleman and convert to her R. Highneſs Favour and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who complains (and Mr. <hi>J.</hi> conceives not without Ground) of wrongs and ſnares from my L. of <hi>W.</hi> againſt his Life, who for his quality and unblameableneſs (confeſſed by his Adverſaries) was uſeful while encouraged to prevent the growth of Popery (which Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> had ſpecial Orders to Endeavour) in his R. Highneſs's Family, whereof he had Charge of Souls, &amp; by that, &amp; other Inſtances, did effect (with Gods aſſiſtance) in good part.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63595:16"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2dly.</hi> when his R. Highneſs began kindly and frequently to mention Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> his performance of his Duty with him in his Dangers at Sea, and eſpecially when his ſacred Majeſty and R. Highneſs were pleaſed to take notice of him in the Royal Chappel in time of Divine Service in view of many, my Lord of <hi>Winton</hi> from that time never ceaſed to employ his utmoſt Power, and intereſt to ruine Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> in Court and Country.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> Therefore doth Humbly deſire the Right Reverend Biſhops of <hi>Bangor</hi> and St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> to cauſe this matter to be ſearch'd by competent Authority, as in their Wiſdoms they ſhall think fit, leaſt there be any Deſign laid againſt the Church, or Judgements be multiplied upon the Nation by unſincere Oaths, or the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Party bear away the Glory of defending the Proteſtant intereſt, and the late glorious King's Cauſe and Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom receive Wrong, or Old Fears and jealouſies be juſtified.</p>
                  <p>And particularly leaſt by any misinformation Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> be oppreſſed by the Church, for his Fidelity to the Church as well againſt the Schiſmatical Intereſt, when it formerly prevailed, as againſt the Popiſh, when it began clandeſtinly to prevail. <hi>Tho. Jones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But my Dioceſan made no regard notwithſtanding of this Information under my hand, only ſent up a Coppy thereof atteſted by a <hi>Publi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Notary,</hi> as the <hi>Notary</hi> himſelf told me.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Hilary</hi> term following, I went to <hi>London</hi> to purſue my Appeal, where after ſome ſpace, I was Arreſted by the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> upon an Action of <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> and courſely uſed.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Term he put in his Declaration for the words. He is a Promotor of Popery, and a ſubverter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as ſpoken by me at <hi>Lanunnis, October</hi> 3. 1668. I told his Agent that I did not ſpeak, nor own ſuch words; But the Biſhops proved them for him at <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and a Verdict of 317 <hi>l.</hi> recovered thereupon againſt me in <hi>February</hi> 1670, and my Rectory Sequeſtred, alſo my Houſe ſeiz'd and abuſed, and Family turn'd out of Doors by an obſolete Writ <hi>vi Laica Amovenda,</hi> to ſupply their Writ of Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Glebelands plowed, and all held from me for Three years without any Contene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Allowance whatſoever, (whereby I was much diſabled to maintain my Appeal) till his Agents received near Twice his Verdict, as was prov'd at <hi>Kings-Bench.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When they had wreſted my Calling and Living from me, they ſet friends upon me, to perſwade me to ſubmit, and ask forgivoneſs, for the words I never ſpoke, nor own'd, and to recede from the Paper under my hand, which I over own'd, and was now more confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in by the Rumour'd Apoſtacy of the Dutcheſs in 1671. which I did ſuſpect and fear from 1666.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch importunities of Friends and Superiors, with offers of Remiſſion, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I never could ſhake off till I declared my Reſolution to his Highneſs in this Paper following.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>My laſt Addreſs to the Duke, <date>April 20. 1673.</date>
                  </head>
                  <head>The Submiſſion of <hi>Tho. Jones;</hi> with his humble requeſt to his R. Highneſs.</head>
                  <p>HAving ſerv'd your Highneſs with my utmoſt love and fidelity to the beſt of my Skill and judgment, as I ought, it was my fate to be approv'd by your Princely knowledg, and ſuddenly deſtroyed upon hear-ſay.</p>
                  <p>Neither find I any hope left, after many years patience, of recovering your promiſed favour, as long as your Highneſs is politickly poſſeſſed, that I refuſe to ſubmit to the Biſhops, againſt all that I have, or can ſpeak, or act to the contrary, unleſs your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would admit me to ſubmit to their Lordſhips (or their Proxies) in your Highneſs preſence, that your Highneſs your ſelf may ſee, and be ſatisfied, as well with my ſubmiſſion, as I hope you are, with my Innocence and Integrity.</p>
                  <p>The number of my Submiſſions tender'd from time to time, (eſteem'd ſatisfactory in the judgment of Gentry, Clergy, Lawyers, Civilians, Biſhops, Nobles) I have made known to the R. Bp. of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> as alſo my manner of Life and Loyalty, for 20 or 30 years paſt, and the paſſages of my calling with <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> in his Circuits, againſt his execrable Act, to ſupport the Loyalty of my Country-men againſt him, (which was not the way in thoſe days to thrive) But his Lordſhip is ſlow, or loath to make his report to your Highneſs, in a concern of his Reverend Brethren, whom neither Innocence nor Submiſſion, nor Interceſſion, nor ſatisfaction, nor the Example of His Majeſty in Pardoning, nor any method whereby God is reconciled to man, or men to one another, could in Seven years appeaſe or reconcile.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63595:17"/>
                  <p>If it be expected, that I am to bear falſe Teſtimony againſt my ſelf, and acknowledge my ſelf guilty, where I know, and am known to be innocent, to juſtify any thereby that have accuſed me wrongfully, and againſt their knowledge of my innocence, to my Prince and Maſter, meerly to prevent the effects of his freſh favour towards me, or for ſome other intrigue, then I plainly declare, that I hold this to be unnatural, and ſlaviſh, and ſinful for me to do, and Satanical for any to expect it: And do remit and quit the hopes of your Highneſſes favour, if it is to be obtain'd upon no other terms. Nevertheleſs in common ordinary juſtice between any Maſter and Servant, your Highneſs may well grant me theſe Three requeſts following, which I humbly make to your Highneſs.</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) My arrear of Salary, and alſo of Chamber Rent, which are about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>l.</hi> for I have not had 6 <hi>d.</hi> allowed me from my Living theſe 2 or 3 years, to buy me Bread, nor the Liberty of my calling to Earn it.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) Your Highneſs Paſs, Certificate, or dimiſſory letter to look out a New Patron, for otherwiſe men fear and ſhun me, for fear of ſome perſonal diſpleaſure in your Highneſs towards me.</p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) Some Equitable Compenſation for my detriment and loſs, for it is well known that I am (in all probability), about 600 <hi>l. per annum</hi> the worſe by accepting your Higneſſes Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and waving the preſent Primate of <hi>Irelands,</hi> and about 500 <hi>l.</hi> out of Purſe the worſe by the Living in <hi>Wales,</hi> and the ſnares and contrived troubles that attend it, (more intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than Death) &amp; laſting upon me about 7 years (which is Life in Law) under the Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Reading-Pew, and raſh words, manag'd by Power againſt me. And I ſhall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I added, to Sir <hi>A. A.</hi> (to make him witneſs of this Addreſs.)</p>
                  <p>That I am, and was of opinion ever, from 1665. that the true cauſes of my Troubles, were not any of thoſe things Objected againſt me by my Lord of <hi>Winton</hi> or any other; but, my excecuting her late Highneſſes Orders againſt Popery, in her Family, and my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to be conſiderable in his Higeneſſes Favour after my attendance at Sea.</p>
                  <p>The Dukes Anſwer to me by Sir <hi>A. A.</hi> and my Lord C. <hi>Auguſt</hi> 14. 1673. The Duke is willing, but is not able to do any thing for you, but as the Bps direct him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I delivered likewiſe to Sir <hi>A. A.</hi> a Certificate of Mr. <hi>Wren,</hi> Secretary to the late Chancellor <hi>Hide,</hi> touching my Actings and ſufferings in times of Uſurpation, as alſo a ſtate of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts and arrears which I left with him.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>A Letter to the Biſhop of <hi>Winton, July 6. 75.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOU were pleaſed (for ſome occult cauſe) to continue an endleſs enmity againſt me, now about Ten years, like the Goddeſs in the Poets, (<hi>quam nec longa Dies, Pietas nec mitigat ulla,</hi> &amp;c.) though Innocent and Infinitely an unequal Match to your Lordſhip, and all along kneeling to your Power. Neither do I remember any advantage, or Victory you ever gain'd over me, but when I laid down my defence and guard at your feet, truſting to your Lordſhip and your R. Brethrens words and Counſel, out of entire reſpect to your Dignities and Perſons: and being now neceſſitated to be Plt. and to take a little benefit of the Law againſt you, you preſently take Sanctuary in your Priviledges againſt me, tho' in a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy firſt begun by your Lordſhip. And after diſowning your Meſſages by Mr. <hi>Markham,</hi> and Mr. <hi>J.</hi> Apothecary (through your Secretary) which they ſtill avow, you lately ſent another to me, by my R. Dioceſan, the Bp. of <hi>Bangor,</hi> which if it be ſtood to, by your Ldp. or Rightly underſtood by me, implies that your Ldp. is willing to forgive me your verdict Moneys, if I acknowledge that I wrong'd your Ldp. which ſignifies to me in effect, that if I wrongfully accuſe my ſelf to juſtifie your Ldp. who have ſo accuſed me to the Duke (to my greater prejudice than you are now able to repair) that then your Ldp. will beſtow that Monys upon me, which you declared at <hi>Kings-Beneh,</hi> and by other Acts and Deeds, to have beſtowed on <hi>Bangor</hi> Church. My Lord, I am ready to do my Duty without Hire, and any thing Elſe, (to recover your Ldps. Peace and Charity,) but ſin, as you find in my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by Mr. <hi>Markham,</hi> for your Ldps ſatisfaction. My Ld. I have lately made 2 or 3 requeſts to his Highneſs, that his Highneſs would be pleaſed to pay me the remaining part of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, and Grant me a Dimiſſory Letter, or recommend me to ſome new Patron; that he would make me ſome equitable reparation for my great detriment occaſioned by his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Favour. His Highneſſes gratious Anſwer was, that he could do nothing for me, but as he was directed by the Bps. meaning I ſuppoſe, your Ldp. I hope therefore that if your Ldp. will not allow his Highneſs to readmit me to his favour, (which his Higneſs ever was, and is willing to) that you will not Ecclipſe his juſtice from</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>July</hi> 6. 75.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your moſt Humble Servant, <hi>Tho. Jones.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>
                     <hi>For the Right Reverend Father in God,</hi> George <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Winton, <hi>at his Houſe in Chelſey, theſe with Reverence.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Biſhop return'd Anſwer to this Letter, by Mr. <hi>Iſaac W.</hi> to Dr. <hi>J.</hi> that I might have my Moneys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd, and what elſe I deſir'd, if I ſubmitted to him.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="submissions">
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:63595:17"/>
                        <head>Some Submiſſions tendered in the Controverſy about Reading Pew.</head>
                        <p>THe Biſhop in his anſwer upon Oath, Affirming, he never gave me order to Publiſh the Curate ſeat, as unfit; to prevent all colour of Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I deſired my Advocate to draw ſuch a ſubmiſſion as might fully ſatisfie the Biſhop of <hi>Bangor,</hi> and Sir <hi>Leolin Jenkins</hi> who it enuouſly appeared againſt me at <hi>Doctors Commons</hi> though neither Judge nor Advocate in the Cauſe, but as <hi>Amicus Curiae</hi> as he term'd it, whereupon Dr. L. Now Sir R. L. Drew for me this draught enſuing, of which he ſaid, no Perſon, or Court on Earth could require more. And this I did, becauſe Sir <hi>Leolin</hi> told me, the Duke was offended with me, becauſe I ſubmitted not to the great Biſhops, nor to my own <hi>Dioceſan.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <q>As the caſe ſtands between my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jones</hi> Rector of <hi>Landurnog,</hi> He having publiſhed at the Altar his Dioceſan s Order for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the Reading Seat in the Church of <hi>Landurnog,</hi> as undecent, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, which Order his <hi>Dioceſan</hi> denieth in his Anſwer in the <hi>Arches</hi> Court, to have given him, This is humbly propoſed in behalf of Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> as a way to extinguiſh all Imputations of Diſobedience, and to end all differences between his <hi>Dioceſan</hi> and him, <hi>viz.</hi> in regard he is convinced in his Conſcience, that he publiſhed but the Truth, he may be allowed to declare it at the ſame Altar upon his voluntary Oath, That he delivered nothing to his Pariſhioners but what his <hi>Dioceſan</hi> gave him Order to do, or what he apprehended to be his <hi>Dioceſans</hi> Order, which done, he ſhall openly acknowledge in the ſame place, that it is his Duty to Read in the Seat in queſtion, or in whatever other Seat his <hi>Dioceſan</hi> ſhall think more convenient.</q>
                        <p>But no ſubmiſſion of this Nature for Peace ſake, would be admitted, though it was tendered in the Courts of <hi>Bangor,</hi> and <hi>Arches,</hi> and <hi>Delegates,</hi> and judg'd ſufficient by Perſons of all Qualities, Divines, Civilians, Gentlemen, Noblemen, Biſhops; But it was expected and inſiſted by Sir <hi>Leulin</hi> and his party, that I ſhould acknowledg, that I had abſolutely diſobeyed my <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> (and was ſorry for it) which I, and my Pariſhioners knew to be falſe, and I ſaw it rended to make me Guilty of the violation of my Canonical Oath, and thereby to Invalidate my Teſtimony for ever againſt the Biſhop, whom I ſuſpected of Perverting the late Dutcheſs in her Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore I was reſolved to adhere to my Innocence and the Truth to the End, againſt all proſpect of Relief from Man.</p>
                        <p>In fine, when they had Wreſted my Eſtate and Galling from me, and I ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to ſubmit, notwithſtanding all threats, and kind offers, they proceeded at laſt to deprive me of my Liberty, and when I was Informed of their Writs of <hi>Excomunicato capiendo</hi> iſſued out into the Country, in order to put me to farther Charges, and to ſeize me at laſt here at <hi>London,</hi> I prevented that trouble to them and my ſelf, by this Surrender to the chief Biſhop-Delegate and my unkind old Friend Sir <hi>Leolin Jenkins,</hi> one of the Chief Sollicitors in this Cauſe, <hi>July</hi> 2. 1672.</p>
                        <p>Whereas I ſtand Excommunicate and Liable to Impriſonment, for not paying certain Charges recovered againſt me, in the Honourable Court of Delegates, to the Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi> and Wardens of <hi>Landurnog,</hi> and it is well known that my Living of <hi>Landurnog</hi> hath been for theſe two years and above ſequeſtred by the ſaid Eiſhop, for the uſe of the Biſhop of <hi>Winton,</hi> ſo that I receive not one Peny of the Profits thereof, and have no other Benefice or preferment to ſubſiſt on.</p>
                        <p>This is humbly to ſignify to the Honourable Court of Delegates, that in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to their Sentence, I ſhall at there call (becauſe of my preſent Diſabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to depoſite ready Mony) Surrender my Self to Priſon, at their Pleaſure, that they may not uſe Bayliffs, or force to take me, for I hear Writs are Ihuing forth to that purpoſe.</p>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:63595:18"/>
                        <p>Or be willing that the ſaid Biſhop of <hi>Bangor,</hi> pay himſelf the ſaid Charges, out of the firſt Profits, as ſhall be due to me out of the ſaid Living; or ſooner, if my Lord of <hi>Winton</hi> give leave.</p>
                        <p>And I do further moſt humbly Declare, that I am very ſorry, it is conceived, or imputed to me, to have diſobeyed my <hi>Dioceſan</hi> in the leaſt, it being againſt my Oath and Principles to be diſobedient to Superiors. And ſhall therefore when reſtored to my Living, be willing to leave my own Seat again, and as far as ſight and light will give Leave, Read Prayers again in the other Seat, which as I now apprehend is <hi>determined</hi> to be the intended, and moſt convenient place to Read Service in, by the Biſhops Affirmation, I before apprehending in my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before God, that my <hi>Dioceſan</hi> gave me his Command to Publiſh the ſame in my Church to be undecent and unfit to Read Prayers in, upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of me, and my Pariſhioners.</p>
                        <p>And I do promiſe to uſe all care and waryneſs to prevent the like miſtake of my Dioceſans Orders for the future.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>For the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>Leolin Jenkins</hi> at <hi>Doctors-Commons.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Was forc'd to take notice, that in the Grand Controverſie about Reading Pew (parallell'd of late to the Tranſgreſſion in Paradice, as if it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd a new <hi>Meſſiah</hi>) you were greatly intruſted and engaged againſt me, by my Adverſaries, not only by your voluntary Pleading without a Call, but alſo by your reſtleſs egging on the ſlow-pac'd Sollicitor to hunt me out of my Livelyhood, whereof the one ſeem'd below your Dignity, and neither part well agreeable with that converſe or friendſhip which on my part to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you was ever ſincere. You left room thereby to conjecture, that you were acted herein by an Obligation, to which Morality, and Inclination, were in worldly prudence to give place. <hi>Tantaene animis Coeleſlibus irae?</hi> Can <hi>Grace</hi> and Serenity be ſo implacably bent for about Seven years together, to oppreſs and ruine, for no original Cauſe, or Provocation, but that the kind Prince was inclined to exalt one's Sheaf. O! ye Judges, and Gods, Learn to do as you would be done by, though there were no <hi>Adonibezek</hi> for an Example.</p>
                  <p>To prevent Charge and trouble, and the Indignity of being purſued with Swords and Clubs, I have directed to you the enclos'd ſurrender, who ſtand ſo near my chiefeſt Adverſaries, to give your Inſtrumental activity, and Powerful intermedling, the honour of the laſt Stroke, and final Conqueſt over me. For being, by Arts and Power, interrupted of the Prince's coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and external reputation; of all maintenance and livelyhood, which is Life and Blood; of Function and Communion, which is dearer than Life; I had nothing left to part with, to ſatiate my enemies thirſt, but my Liberty; which being now ſurrender'd, betokens a near approach of detection and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, if Truth, and Innocence, and Truſt in God, can never be ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as I believe they cannot.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall therefore be ready to obey your call, or thoſe that entruſt you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in what warning you pleaſe to ſend, or leave, at the <hi>Eagle and Child</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> where you ſhall find, or hear from</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>July 2. 1672.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63595:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Death of my Dioceſan, and an Act of Oblivion ſhortly enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, delivered me from this preſent trouble about the Reading Pew, and likewiſe from the Coſts, which the Delegates declar'd at the time of their Sentence, ſhould not be allowed at all to the Church-Wardens, nor to the Biſhop of <hi>Bangor,</hi> but on Condition, to be refunded again to me upon my ſubmiſſion; which the Biſhops death, and the Act of Grace ſupplied; as was acknowledged.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="memorandum">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Orders from her Late Highneſs in 1664. to me, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the growth of Popery in her Family, deliver'd to me by the R. Biſhop of</hi> Wincheſter <hi>to Tranſcribe, and the Original to be reſtored to him, for Reaſons beſt known to himſelf.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>I.</hi> TO enter upon Reading Prayers every Morning at Seven a Clock, beſide the other hours of Ten.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>II.</hi> To procure a Liſt of all the Family that are Book'd from Sir <hi>H de Vic</hi>'s Office, or Sir <hi>Allen Apſly.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>III.</hi> To make another Liſt of thoſe that are not Book'd, and of all Children and Servants that pertain to any of the D's Family.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>IV.</hi> To know diſtinctly the Profeſſion of each perſon, whether of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or the <hi>Roman.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>V.</hi> To oblige all the Servants, &amp;c. whoſe imploiment will not permit them to attend the other hour, to be at the Morning Prayers at Seven a Clock.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>VI.</hi> To have a care that others who are free, obſerve the other hour of Prayer, and to admoniſh them if they do not.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>VII.</hi> To diſpenſe with the abſence of either ſort rarely on the Week days, but not at all, if in health, on <hi>Sundays.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>VIII.</hi> Thoſe who are refractory or uncounſellable, to preſent a Schedule of their names to her Highneſs.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>IX.</hi> To Catechiſe and inſtruct the <hi>Pages</hi> and others who want inſtruction, very conſtantly, according to the Orders of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>X.</hi> To have a particular eye of the Pages, as well the Dukes as Dutcheſs, to keep them ſteady in our Religion, her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs being inform'd, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſts find oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of diſcourſing with them, and to find what you can of their private conferences.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>XI.</hi> To oblige all the Congregation to be conſtant at Evening-Prayer
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63595:19"/>as well as Morning, and if their due imployments will not permit them to attend an Hour, to chuſe an Hour convenient for them, and in that oaſe to Read twice in the Afternoon as well as in the Morning.</item>
                        </list>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="observations">
                        <head>Obſervations on theſe ORDERS.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. HER Highneſs was acquainted, by my means, of the Practices of the other Chappel, upon Young, and Sick, and the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sex, in and about St. <hi>James</hi>'s, to obtain her countenance to ſupport me in my Duty.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The firſt Order tended to bring me and the Liturgy into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, for on Seven in the Morning on <hi>Sundays,</hi> all choſe to go to the Morning Sermon at <hi>White hall;</hi> and this was never us'd, atter I was remov'd.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The forth tended to enrage ſeveral in the Family againſt me.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. I did begin to Catechiſe, but was diſcouraged in it by the Arts of the ſaid Biſhop.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="introduction">
                        <head>The Introduction of <hi>Ferdinando De Macedo,</hi> to the late Dutcheſs of <hi>York,</hi> Anno. 1664.</head>
                        <p>HIS Father, <hi>Damiano Rangel De Macedo, Provedor,</hi> or Lord Juſtice of the Province of <hi>Beira Dezembargador,</hi> or Privy Councellor to the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and Chancellor or the Kingdom, dyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Year 1656. Leaving Iſſue.</p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. <hi>Antonius de Silveira de Macedo,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Ferdinandus Rangell de Macedo,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. <hi>Coſmo Rangel de Macedo,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>4. <hi>Donna Iſabella de Moira.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                        <p n="1">1. <hi>Antonius</hi> the Eldeſt, was Admiral of their <hi>Brazil</hi> Armada in their War againſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> he ſank himſelf and his Ship, in a Sea-fight, with <hi>Blake,</hi> when over pour'd in their War with <hi>Cromwel.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2. <hi>Ferdinandus,</hi> now the Eldeſt, a Monk.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. <hi>Coſmo.</hi> 18. Year old, now the Hoir. At preſent a Student at Law: <hi>Anno.</hi> 25. of his Age, He will be Chancellor of the Kingdom of courſe, by the Kings Favour to that Family for theſe 100. Years, his Uncle at preſent is Chancellor in his ſlead, and his Governour.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. <hi>Donna Iſabella</hi> Married to <hi>Andraeas de Carvelioſa,</hi> a Privy Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and Son to the Preſident of the Kings Council.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ferdinandus</hi> was brought up in the Schools of the Jeſuits at <hi>Lisbone,</hi> Commenc'd Batchelor at Law at the Univerſity of <hi>Coimbria,</hi> became a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Recolet at 18 Years of Age, continued 20. is now 43 Years, Old. He was Chaplain and Kinſman to the <hi>Portugal</hi> Ambaſſador, SA, here in <hi>Cromwels</hi> time for 3 Years: For 3 Years Miſſionary in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> whither he travail'd by Sea and Land, having viewed the <hi>Holy Land</hi> in his Courſe; Accuſed before the Cardinals for laying aſide
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63595:19"/>Images (wherewith he ſaw the Heathens ſcandaliz'd, a Preacher in <hi>Rome</hi> for divers years, Preached ſeveral times before <hi>Allexander</hi> and <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> Popes. He was Guardian of the great Monaſtry of <hi>Piſae</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> Miſſionary in <hi>Fandors,</hi> for 3 Years, and Miſſionary in <hi>Languedoc,</hi> in <hi>Frunce. He conceal'd as yet his Relation to the Queen, he e in</hi> England, <hi>as Clerk of her Cloſet, and how he Preach'd againſt Invocation of Saints upon St.</hi> Ulſulas<hi>'s day, and was ſent to</hi> Rome <hi>with Letters, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the Contents became a</hi> Proteſtant <hi>in France,</hi> where (he declared) he was taken upon the King of <hi>France</hi> his Edict againſt Apoſtates, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenc'd to death by the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Tholous,</hi> upon his Appeal delivered, becauſe no Subject of <hi>France</hi> He was Impriſoned and chain'd, Arms, Legs, and Neck, by the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>Conti,</hi> but would not <hi>turn</hi> for fair or fowl means, he is conveyed by a Party of 25 men towards <hi>Catalonia,</hi> to be delivered to the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſiton:</hi> Reſcued by a <hi>Switzer</hi> Collonel on the way, a Proteſtant, and one that knew him. Liv'd in Woods for a Quartor of a Year, got over to <hi>England</hi> in <hi>November</hi> 1663. Liv'd in obſcurity, want, and Sickneſs for half a year; In the mean time ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited by the Queens Chaplain, with large offers from the Queen, and of Pardon from the Pope; The Queens Confeſſor, his Tutor, Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to return in the name of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> &amp;c. And that they Faſted and Prayed in the Queens Chappel for his recovery to their Church; againſt all which he ſtood out, living upon Bread and Water, till his Caſe, by good Providence to him, came to be made known to the late Dutcheſs of <hi>York,</hi> which was upon this occaſion.</p>
                        <p>The Noble Lord <hi>B</hi> accompanying his Lady near her time at a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at St. <hi>James</hi>'s on <hi>Eaſter day</hi> (where I Preached, and celebrated) greatly enlarg'd the uſual offering, and Appointed me ſhortly after to Chriſten his ſecond Son, now his Eldeſt, and Lord <hi>B.</hi> And ordered me by his Secretary Mr <hi>Aldridge</hi> Ten pound for the ſame, Five pound to my ſelf, and the other Five pound by my hands, to what poor I pleaſ'd, concealing his Lordſhips Name; Enquiring for a fit object, and moſt remote from private Ends, for ſo generous a Charity, I was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to a ſtranger at the <hi>Fox</hi> in <hi>Drury Lane,</hi> that was believed to be a Gentleman, and in great Want and Miſery, and with little Engliſh to make his caſe known: who happened to be this <hi>Ferdinandus de Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do;</hi> I took this Examination of him, or the moſt part thereof, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Dutcheſs of <hi>York</hi> being acquainted was greatly pleas'd, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially with the paſſage about a Faſt in the Queens Chappel, for ſhe ſaid, ſhe knew that they had a Faſt in their Chappel, about a Month before for a loſt Sheep, but could never find before, who it was; and ſhe liberally relieved him, by the hands of the Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> as did others by her Example, and Ordered me to found the Prieſts of the other Chappel, what Exceptions they had againſt him, and I found they had none at laſt, either againſt his Birth, or Life, but only his Revolt from them.</p>
                        <p>Then one was ſent by her Highneſs to the Biſhops, to know in what manner he was to be received, who returned ſad, and Blank, with a Story there told, that there was no great difference between the two Religions, and that two Brothers had converted one another, the Papiſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and the Proteſtant the Papiſt, which was the firſt time I did ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63595:20"/>Danger from the ſaid Biſhops, which no Innocence or Favour of Duke or Dutcheſs, could afterwards avert.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>De Macedo</hi> is order'd to go for <hi>Oxford,</hi> againſt his will, (under colour to be preſerved from the threats of the Queens Chaplains, to whom he was an Eye-ſore, whom he did not fear) being to be there maintained upon the Contribution of the Dutcheſs, Arch-Biſhop, and Biſhop of <hi>Winton,</hi> the Dutcheſs ſincerely then at his departure, advizing him, to be conſtant to us, and ſhe would be conſtant to him: But in <hi>Oxon</hi> ſeveral miſcarriages were ſoon laid to his Charge, and I was blamed for appearing for him, and by the Biſhop of <hi>Winton</hi>'s Order Writ this following Letter to <hi>Oxon</hi> to him.</p>
                        <floatingText type="letter">
                           <body>
                              <p>DIſſimulare ultra non potui, Egregie Domine, nec debui forſan, creber. rimos hos nuntios, huc nuper allatos, Criminum non Levium exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationi tuae adhaerentium; quod, exemplo Academicis periculoſiſſimo, illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citis compotationibus, Pictiſ<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> chartis, honores Principum &amp; Studendi ſpatia turpiter impendas, &amp; leviter offendentibus cultros paſſim at<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> Pugiones mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteris, nec a ſacro nomine temere <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpando temperes: ut ambigere aliquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties adigas candidiſſimos judices, qua fidei Integritate Patrios, nec corruptos mores deſerueris. Quod<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> Natalitiorum Hiſtoriam, Dictorum<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> fidem omnem intentat adhuc at<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> Labefactat, Oratoris Luſitani te ſacellanum Commentus ſis, cum nec eſſes, alius eſſet. Ego ut has maculas videam atq agnoſcam, enecor, cum Adducor, cum nullas, hic dum eſſes, deprehenderim, &amp; diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contra Praecaverim, at<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> ob eam quam oſtenderas animi deiq: fiduciam, alieniſſimum crediderim. Adeo ut, Gallorum Elogiis, Popularium artibus, &amp; Providentiae miraculis, ulterius inſignitum, Illuſtriſſimae Heroinae Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Duci Eboracenſi Commendatiſſimum exoptatiſſimum<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> dare, non dubitave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim. Ipſe, at ſtylo proprio, aut alterius vitae conſcii, authoritate, aut Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum hic Interpretum ope, melius eluas at<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> depellas, graviter conſulo, imo benevolentiae jure, expecto, quam &amp; tibi ſemper habui Integerrimam, &amp; non immerenti aeternum, habiturum praeſto.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <dateline>Ex Aedibus ſcti <hi>Jacobi,</hi> 
                                    <date>
                                       <hi>Oct. 22. 1664.</hi>
                                    </date> 
                                    <hi>For his much reſpected Friend</hi> Don Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando de Macedo at Ch. Ch. <hi>In Oxon:</hi>
                                 </dateline>
                                 <signed>Tui Studioſiſſimus Tho. Jones.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                        <floatingText type="letter">
                           <body>
                              <head>To which he returned this Anſwer,</head>
                              <opener>
                                 <salute>Domine &amp; Amice.</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>LIteras a Londino Accepi, quibus mihi innoteſcit, me paſſim; &amp; in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus libet platearum Angulis tanquam furentem leonem &amp; Rabidam Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grida deſcribi, ſed noſeas, nec te lateat, Omnia venanata tela, orbiſ<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> bilem, a me Extorquere non poſſe virtutem meam quae altius in me Radices egit quam ut iſtis procellis, aut minitante Fortuna, quaſſari valeat. Hae jam ſunt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae literae quas ad te reſcribo; Credideram me in aquam ſcripſiſſe, &amp; lineas in arena Duxiſſe, cum ne verbum quidem a te receperim. Semper te ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimaram mihi amicum; ſed jam video jam ſcenam mutatam eſſe, &amp; pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus te diverſa opinari, quam mihimet perſuaſeram; Cum jam ad me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feratur te paenitere, quod unquam mihi favorem ullum impartitus ſis; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi multorum auxilio opus fuit, ut in Dominae Ducis gratiam &amp; Patrocinium in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63595:20"/>Sed tu ſolus inſtar omnium potes in me Celſitudinis ſuoe rugas &amp; ſup er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia contrahere. Vix tamen mihimet perſuadere poſſum te Velle deprimere &amp; in proeceps deturbare, quem adeo Magnifice Extuliſti; tibi eſt fovere &amp; protegere, quem benigne, ut ita Dicam, plantaſti, contra omnium Invidorum, Spicula Spero me Londinum cito profecturum, Salutesquaeſo humiliter Dominam Kylvert.</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>Tibi Divinctiſſimus, &amp; Humilimus ſervus. De Macedo</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                        <p>Whereby I perceiv'd his Letters to me were intercepted and the poor. Stranger unjuſtly traduced and abuſ'd, as was well atteſted to me. Mr. <hi>G.</hi> being ſet on (among other Snares) to moleſt and affront him, which he had both Strength and Courage to reſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>After I went to Sea, in <hi>November</hi> following, with the Duke, he was ſoon ſent for up to <hi>London,</hi> and Spirited into <hi>France,</hi> where he was reliev'd by my Lord <hi>Hollis,</hi> and had a Miraculous eſcape at <hi>Portsmouth</hi> in his return, (which was well atteſted) ſome great Perſons of both Churches diſcovered and Named, who conſpired together, to have him ſent into <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> to be burnt.</p>
                        <p>The Dutcheſs upon his return to <hi>London,</hi> deſerted him, and M. D. his good Friend was alienated from him. <hi>C. P. Miles Veteranus</hi> a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,</hi> and a ſuſpected Prieſt, with whom I had acquaintance formerly in <hi>Wales,</hi> telling me in <hi>Weſtmiſter-Hall,</hi> now <hi>Macedo</hi> is a Confeſſor of your Church, who owns him? doth the Dutcheſs of <hi>York,</hi> or Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> or Arch Biſhop of <hi>C. C?</hi> which proved too true. And though I was but lately return'd from Sea, and in ſpecial Favour with both their Highneſſes, I was nevertheleſs, by the means of the Dutcheſs and Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> and Arch-Biſhop, ſuddenly diſmiſſ'd from the Dukes Service, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will, and Divers reſolutions to the contrary, with diſgrace and ruine, notwithſtanding all interceſſions, and clear'd Innocence in my behalf: And <hi>Macedo</hi> Scandaliz'd, went over to the Diſſenters, for ſaid he to me in his free ſtile; <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> W. <hi>Nec habet anima, neque Dignitatem;</hi> and liv'd for about Ten years under various reports at <hi>London,</hi> after he had been burnt for <hi>Sodomy</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> as afore, and the Perſecution afterwards turn'd and continued by the Biſhop of <hi>W.</hi> againſt me for many Years.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
